歡迎收看史丹佛大學公開課
本字幕由志願者義務貢獻
Welcome to Stanford CS193P,this is winter quarter 2015.
歡迎參加史丹佛大學 2015 年冬季學期的 CS193P 課程
And we're gonna dive right in today to some brief slide work.
我們首先簡要地概覽一下今天課程的內容
This people at Stanford, you've got a document that describe, describes all the grading and all that stuff
在座的同學，你們手裡都有一份敘述評分標準的文件，
so I'm not gonna go over that in lecture like I often do to start the quarter.
所以我不想像以往開課時那樣再重覆說明一遍
Instead I'm gonna talk a little bit about, what this class is about.
相反，我首先要談一談，這門課到底是有關什麼的
Brief mention of the prerequisites cuz they're pretty important in this class.
接下來簡單會提到學習本課程的先修課程，因為這對於本課程滿重要的
Then just the quickest overview of iOS.
然後會對 iOS 進行一個快速預覽
I'm gonna assume that anyone who is here or is watching this, knows what that is.
我想假定在座的和觀看影片的各位同學，都知道那是什麼吧
And then, we're gonna dive right into a big old demo.
接下來，我們將會進入一個大的舊的 demo
It's gonna be a two-day thing, where I'm really going to try and
這個會用兩節課內容，在這裡裡我會試著
introduce you to Xcode and the development environment and
向你們介紹Xcode、開發環境以及
this language Swift, that you're gonna have to learn to develop for iOS.
程式語言 Swift，這是當你在iOS上開發時將會需要學的
All right, so what is this class about?
好的，那麼本課程是關於什麼的呢？
It's about building cool apps, as we know.
這門課是有關於開發超酷的App，正如我們所知道的
Why are these iOS apps so cool?
為什麼這些 iOS Apps這麼酷呢？
Well, because the device you're gonna run them on is in your pocket or
因為執行這些Apps的設備要不是在你的口袋裡，
in your backpack.
不然就在你的背包裡
Either, if you write an app, you can just pull it out and show your friends and
又或者，如果你寫了一個App，你可以把它發佈出來，然後秀給你的朋友看
it's highly networked and incredible graphics with animation.
它高度地網路化，而且有令人驚奇的動畫圖形效果
It's just cool all the way around and I think you guys all know that or you wouldn't be here.
它在各個方面都很 cool 我想你們應該都知道這些，否則你們就不會坐在這裡了
But you're also gonna learn in this class a lot of real life Object-Oriented Programming.
在這們課程中，你們也需要學習一些關於面向對象編程的知識
You're taking a lot of other classes here at Stanford on things like graphics, and
你們也可能在史丹佛參加過一些關於圖形、
networking, and databases, and maybe animation. Things like that.
網絡、數據庫也許還有動畫方面的課程
And we're gonna is kinda tie that all together into a real world class.
然而我們將這些內容融合在一起，
'Kay? You're gonna get to see all this stuff.
你們會在本課程內看到所有這些東西
Now, you know, it's gonna be kind of a survey course in that,
現在，你應該知道這會是一個概述型課程，
I can't go too deep into networking. I can't go too deep into databases.
我不會深入講述網絡的內容，我不會深入講述數據庫的內容，
I can't go too deep into animation, but you'll get to see it all in a really real
我不會深入講述動畫的內容，但是你們會在
world environment, where people out there building apps using that technology.
真實項目的環境中用到所有的這些技術
For some of you who haven't seen that before that'll be a big bonus of this class, I think.
我認為，對於一些之前沒有接觸過這些的同學，本課程對他們會有很大的提升
The prerequisites of this class.
學習本課程的先決條件
Number one thing is you have to be a pretty strong Object-Oriented programmer.
最重要的，你需要有很好的面向對象編程功底
If you're not a strong Object-Oriented programmer, and
如果你不是，
you hit this class, you're probably gonna go under water, pretty quick.
還選了這個課，你可能很快就會掉隊了
Okay? I'm gonna assume you know, everything about Object-Oriented Programming.
我假設你已經瞭解關於面向對象編程的一切
iOS is a completely Object-Oriented Programming envir, development environment.
iOS 是一個完全的面向對象編程的開發環境
I just don't mean I'm not just talking about the language is Object-Oriented.
我的意思不只是說程式語言是面向對象的
But the entire design of it the way you use it if you're not
在你使用過程中，它的整個設計方式都是面向對象的 如果你
comfortable with things like subclassing and
不熟悉類似於子類之類的東西，
stuff like that then you're just really gonna be behind the curve.
那麼你真的有可能真的跟不上了
In iOS so at Stanford here that means CS16A and B or
史丹佛編程相關課程有 CS16A、CA16B、
CS16X, and then you know, CS107, while it's not really Object-Oriented course,
CS16X、以及 CS107，雖然它並不是專門的面向對象課程，
at least it's a heavy duty programming course.
但至少是一門重量級的編程課程
CS108 is a great Object-Oriented course so
CS108 是非常好的面向對象課程
if you have, if you've taken CS108 you'll probably, be really well prepped.
如果你曾經參加過 CS108，你可能已經有了充分的準備
110, again not really too much an Object-Oriented program but
CS110，同樣也沒有太多關於面向對象的知識，
good programming course cuz there's a lot of programming in this class,
但同樣是一門非常好的編程課程，因為其中有大量的編程實踐
in fact, all the work in this class is programming.
事實上，所有這些課程的內容都是關於編程的
You will not have, a little bit of reading the first couple of weeks just to
在頭幾個星期，你們需要為了學習新語言，多做一些閱讀
kinda learn this new language, but it's almost all programming after that all
在這之後，一直到最終的項目，
the way til the end, including your final project.
都需要運用到你新學到的語言進行編程任務
So if you're not really comfortable with all these terms,
所以，如果你真的不適應面向對象編程，
this Object-Oriented terms or if you're just not really comfortable with
或者你真的不太適應寫較大的程序，
writing big programs then this class will definitely be a challenge for you.
那麼這門課程對你來說將是一個巨大的挑戰
okay, so what's in iOS, what are the parts of it?
那麼，iOS 都包括哪些部分呢？
You know, it's ha, it's such a big system, it's got so much in it.
它是一個龐大的系統，其中包含很多部分
It's impossible for me to, like, encapsulate it into a small little summary but.
不太可能能用一兩句話將其表述完整
I do have this slide right here that divides it into these four layers.
我在這個 slides 中，將其分為四層
These four layers are approximately down near the hardware at the bottom.
這四層從靠近硬件的底層，
Up near the user at the top. Okay?
到靠近用戶的頂層
So at the bottom, so
在最下面一層，
a lot of people don't realize that iOS is basically a Unix-based operating system.
很多人沒有注意到，iOS 基本就是一個基於 Unix 的操作系統
'Kay? It's very similar shares a lot of the core of Mac OS X. Okay?
它大量借鑒了 Mac OS X 的內核部分
Now, it's certainly optimized for mobile devices, which have
當然，它專門為在電池等等方面受到限制的移動設備優化過的，
battery restrictions and things like that, but that is basically what it is.
但基本上它仍可看作是一個 Unix 系統
And so down at that layer you've got sockets, and
這樣的話，在這層中包含了 socket（套接字）、
you've got you know, permissions, and things like that,
permission（權限） 等等類似的部分
that have to be near the oh you know, hardware to, to work properly.
它靠近底層硬件，並保證其正常工作
But above that there's kind of an Object-Oriented layer that lets you get at
在這之上，是一個能夠讓你使用大量的面向對象編程技術的
a lot of that stuff using Object-Oriented Programming.
面向對象的層
'Kay? And this stuff is not UI oriented it's
但是這層不包含 UI
more kind of accessing the hardware through Object-Oriented Programming or
其更多用於通過面向對象的編程方式訪問硬件，
accessing networking through Object-Oriented Programming but
或者訪問網絡，等等
it's a big layer there and so we will spend a fair amount of
它是一個很大的層，我們將花大量時間在該層上，
time in this layer because we need those primitives to build at the higher layers.
因為我們需要這些原始組件來建立更高的層
Then, there's this whole layer, which I wish we had more time to spend on.
我希望我們有更多時間花在這一層，
We only get ten weeks in this whole class.
但是我們的課程只有十周
It goes by so fast, you'll be amazed, as you're probably, used to with your Stanford courses.
在史丹佛的課程中，你會感嘆時間過得如此之快
But there's a whole media layer here, both for
再往上，是一整個媒體層，
static images, as you know, JPEG and things like that.
包括比如你們熟悉的 JPEG 等的靜態圖像，
And video both capturing video, editing video, all that.
包括拍攝影片、編輯影片等的影片處理，
Incredible audio, the frameworks on this device for doing 3D audio for games and all that.
不可思議的音頻框架，用於處理 3D 音效，以及遊戲等等
I get to, unfortunately I get to very little of this layer.
很不幸，我對這層知道的並不多
But I'll try to let you know, that it's in there and then you'll know to go out and
但是我可以告訴你它裡面有什麼，這樣你用到的時候就可以查閱相關資料，
seek out, if you're building a very audio intensive app or
或者當你正在寫一個用到大量音頻影片技術的應用的時候，
video intensive app, you'll seek out that layer.
你會知道去哪找這些資料
But we'll spend the vast majority of our time at the Cocoa Touch layer.
我們會在 Cocoa Touch 層上花費大量的時間
So the Cocoa Touch layer, that's where the buttons and
Cocoa Touch 層里包含了 button，
sliders and things like that are it's the layer,
slider 等類似的控件，
where you're gonna build the interactivity with your end user.
你可以通過它們來和你的用戶建立互動
And so, that's where we probably spend 70 plus percent of our time in the Cocoa Touch layer.
我們會在 Cocoa Touch 上花費 70% 甚至更多的時間
And this is a very powerful layer.
這也是一個非常強大的層
You know, you've seen things like the maps app on the phone.
你們可能在手機上見過地圖類的應用
There's basically, an object that does almost the entire maps app, that you can
事實上，有一個幾乎完整的地圖應用對象，
just drop right into your program, and now you have maps in your program.
你只需要直接拖進你的程序里，你的程序中就有地圖了
Same thing with web browser.
同樣的還有瀏覽器
If you wanna put web browsing in your app, it's just boom, pop an object in there,
如果你想讓你的應用有瀏覽網頁的功能，那麼僅僅需要拖拽一個對象，
call a couple methods and in your, on your way.
再調用幾個方法即可
So very powerful, very high level in there's a lot going on in there and
所以在強大和高級的 Cocoa Touch ，我們會瞭解很多，
that's where we will spend most of our time, 'kay?
並且在此花費大量的時間
And by the way, if you have any questions I try to glance up, so
順便說一下，我抬眼一瞥的時候，
the bright lights over there sometimes in my way,
有可能會看到你們的提問，但是有時我也會注意不到，
but, shout out or you know, otherwise get my attention.
所以盡量讓我注意到你
If you feel free to interrupt.
如果你感覺打斷我沒什麼問題的話
Then there's the development platform itself.'Kay?
接下來就是開發平台本身
With the tools we use to build these iOS apps.
我們會用這些工具來搭建 iOS 應用
What's in that?
其中都有什麼？
Well, it's all pretty much now been funneled into this one application called Xcode 6.
有很多很棒的工具都集成在 Xcode 6 內
There are some little adjuncts that it calls out to but
可能還有其它一些輔助編程工具，
Xcode 6 is everything, it's your code editor,
但是 Xcode 6，你值得擁有，它是一個代碼編輯器，
it's your compiler, your debugger all of that in one, pretty awesome app.
它是一個編譯器，是一個調試器，總之是一個很棒的應用
And so we'll be learning all about Xcode 6 in this class, and
所以我們這個課程里會講到很多有關 Xcode 6 的知識
that's where you'll be spend all your time developing, you're not gonna be at
而你編程的時候會一直使用 Xcode，你不需要
a terminal typing in Emacs or something, you're gonna be in Xcode 6.
在終端下用 Emacs 或其他的編輯器，你只需要使用 Xcode 6
Languages I have there's actually, two languages in iOS now.
現在可以使用兩種語言開發 iOS 應用
There are peers that you can pretty much use either one.
你可以選擇使用任何一個
One of them is called Objective-C,
其中一個名為 Objective-C，
that's the language that iOS was originally developed for.
它也是 iOS 一直以來使用的開發語言
It's a language been around a long time, probably 30 years it's been around or 25
這個語言已經有大概 25 到 30 年的歷史了，
to 30 years that's it's actually been used to build stuff that's on the Mac today.
人們用它為 Mac 開發應用
So, it's very mature language but it's also 25, 30 years old.
因此，它是非常成熟的語言，但是已經 25，30 歲了
And so Apple last summer introduced a completely new language called Swift, and
所以蘋果公司在去年夏天發佈了一個叫 Swift 的全新的語言，
Swift, you can do pretty much everything in iOS with Swift，
你可以使用 Swift 在 iOS 上開發任何應用，
that's the language we're gonna learn because it's a modern language.
它也是本次課我們要學習的語言，它是一門現代的語言
Apple did a great job of kind of, building all the best stuff of
為了創建 Swift，蘋果公司做了很多工作，
all the languages that have been invented over the last, you know,
它吸收了很多已存在的程式語言的優點
25 years of this especially the last five or ten years into this language.
二十五年以來，特別是近五到十年的語言的優點
It's very concise it's a very type safe language but has type inference and a lot
它語法簡潔，類型安全，並且還有類型推斷以及
of things that make it so that you get the best of both worlds by having type safety-
大量的特性，可以同時擁有類型安全，
And not have to be constantly over specifying everything.
又不需要不斷地指定各種類型
So we're gonna go Swift only, I'm not even gonna really talk about Objective-C,
所以我們只使用 Swift，不會講太多 Objective-C，
I just don't have time to do both languages.
我也沒有時間講兩種語言
Yeah. >>
（學生提問）
>> Yeah, so the question is if I'm going out into the world to do
這個同學的問題是，如果我將步入社會，
iOS development in the real world for real companies.
並想找一份做 iOS 開發的工作，
Am I probably, gonna have to learn Objective-C?
我是否還需要學習 Objective-C？
And the answer is it depends on the company you're at.
答案是，這取決於你的公司
Probably in the short term, yes.
可能在短期內，答案是肯定的
But as the time goes by probably, more and more people switch to siff, Swift.
但是隨著時間的推移，可能有越來越多的人會轉到 Swift
The good thing is the underlying iOS
好消息這兩門語言在 iOS 之下的 API
APIs are exactly the same for both, its just the syntax-
是完全相同的，
Of the language a little bit
僅僅只是語法上
about how the language approaches calling the API is slightly different, but any,
會有略微的不同，但是
everything that you learn in here about the underlying,
你們在這裡學習的 iOS 的部分，
lying parts of iOS will totally work in Objective-C.
使用 Objective-C 完全也可以實現
All the methods are the same you know,
所有的方法都是一樣的，
it's just the syntax is a little different.
僅僅只有語法上的一點區別
So, don't feel too bad about not
所以對於沒有學全兩門語言，
learning both languages, and once you've learned this language,
不要感到沮喪，一旦你掌握了 Swift，
learning Objective-C is gonna be pretty easy, too.
再學 Objective-C 也很快
So. Good question though. All right.
這個問題問得很好
Of course iOS is filled with tons of frameworks.
當然，iOS 內部擁有眾多的框架，
Frameworks are libraries, basically, of objects that you use,
框架就是你會用到的類庫以及基本對象
as building blocks to build your application.
作為搭建你的應用的模塊，
And we are going to be covering them.
我們也會學習它們
UIKit is the main one.
UIKit 就是其中主要的一個
It's got most of the user interface stuff in it.
它包含了大量的關於用戶界面的內容
Foundation is that most the Core Service layer that I was talking about,
在 Core Service 中，我提及最多的就是 Foundation 框架
and but there's tons of other ones, Core Motion for doing the, the device moving
其他還有很多，Core Motion 框架用於處理設備移動、
around, you know, gyro and accelerometer, Core Data for Object-Oriented database.
旋轉、陀螺及加速度等響應，Core Data 框架用於操作面向對象的數據庫，
Things like that.
等等
So I'll get to, as many as those as I can, especially the big ones.
我會盡我所能盡可能多的傳授給你們，特別是那些大的框架
But there's just way too many to cover in ten weeks.
但是這對一個只有十周的課程來說，內容太多了
And finally we I, I put this, as a first class thing with all the rest, as a design strategy MVC.
然而以上的那些東西均不是我們第一課要講的內容 我首先要說的是一個叫做 MVC 的設計模式
I think, I usually ask, I'll all ask this year, too.
每年我都會問，同樣今年我也要問這個問題，
How many people have used MVC in some other class?
你們有多少同學曾經在其他課上用過 MVC？
See, so it's half of you.
哦，有一半的同學
So I'll be teaching MVC, as if you don't know it, so
有同學不知道，那麼我先說說 MVC
if you don't know it don't worry.
就算你不瞭解它，也不用擔心
But MVC is a way of designing your application so that it's a little more
MVC 是你設計應用的一種方式，用它設計的代碼
debuggable, reusable understandable to you and to anyone reading your code.
無論對於你自己或者其他人都具有可讀性，也更易調試，易復用
And iOS was designed with MVC from the start.
而 iOS 從一開始就使用 MVC 設計
So it's just integral part to building an iOS.
而這僅僅是創建一個 iOS 應用整體中的一部分
Now, I'm gonna do the demo today, and on Wednesday I'm kinda not gonna follow MVC.
我要開始做今天的 demo，但是在週三的課上不會使用 MVC
But then next Monday we're gonna apply MVC to the demo I'm doing today and
但是下週一我會應用 MVC 繼續今天的 demo，
Wednesday, so you're gonna get the full MVC treatment there.
週三的時候你們就會對 MVC 有了充分的理解
And I'll be having some slides on MVC on Wednesday to prepare you for next Monday.
然後在週三我會放一些 MVC 的 slides 來為下週一做準備
Okay? All right, so here's the demo.
好，下面開始做 demo
The demo I'm gonna do, is something I actually did a few years ago that really works well-
接下來我要做的 demo，是我前幾年做的一個計算器，運行起來還不錯
With Swift, which is a calculator.
我們用 Swift 來實現它
So, we're gonna build this calculator.
現在，我們來創建這個計算器
And we're gonna build it from scratch, all the way.
我們將從頭開始，一步一步創建它
And I like to do my demos, where I only type in stuff, I don't copy and
我喜歡動手敲代碼來做演示，而不會複製或者
paste big chunks of code in or whatever.
粘貼大段代碼什麼的
I know, I'd see a lot of laptops open, a lot of people like to try and
我知道，我看到很多人已經打開筆記本電腦，很多人都喜歡
follow along with me.
跟著我親自動手嘗試
I'm a fast typer, but usually in most demos you can keep, keep up if you want.
我打字速度很快，但是通常在大多數演示中，只要你想，還是能夠跟上我的速度
I don't recommend it necessarily, or certainly I don't require it.
我並不推薦這麼做，或者說不必要這樣
I am going to, you, you'll be able to go back and watch this particular demo on video.
你們可以回去看影片
Even Stanford people will be able to do that.
史丹佛的學生也可以這麼做
Because your first assignment is gonna be to reproduce what I do.
因為你們的第一次作業是要重現我所做的
'Kay? That is 90% of your first assignment.
這就是你第一次作業的 90%
Reproduce what I'm gonna do, today and on Wednesday.
重現我今天和星期三做的
So I'm not gonna post the code because I want you to go through the experience of
我不會把代碼給你，因為我想讓你自己動手敲代碼
typing the code in, and if you watch in on video,
如果你是在看這個影片，
watching what I do again, and and typing it all in. 'Kay?
看一遍我乾了什麼，然後自己敲代碼
And I'll explain that all on Wednesday. Okay?
我將在週三對所有問題做解釋
So, I put on the slide a bunch of things that I'm gonna cover, but I'm not gonna go
我把一些將要提及的部分放到了 slides 里，但我不會提前
over it in advance, I'm just gonna sit, sit and soon I'll start doing it.
給你們講這些內容 我要坐下，然後開始演示
So any questions before I dive in here?
在這之前還有什麼問題嗎？
I know we're gonna little fast, but I wanna maximize your learning time.
我知道我講得有點快，因為我想最大化你們的學習時間
-（同學提問）
Direct of what?
什麼？
-（同學提問）
So the question is, which Xcode should we use, should you use?
問題是，我們應該用哪個版本的 Xcode？
Well, you should just use the one on the Mac App Store.
你們直接使用在 Mac App Store 上的那個版本就好了
So, just go to the Mac App Store, it's free.
去 Mac App Store 上免費下載
Use the one there, whatever the latest one is.
使用那裡的最新的版本
If a new one comes out in the quarter, well, let's all switch over to it.
如果有更新的版本出來，那麼我們就更新
Okay, let's just always be using the latest Xcode.
總之我們用的是最新版本的 Xcode
'Kay any-
還有問題嗎？
（同學提問）
Not. We're not gonna using a beta or anything like that.
不，我們不用測試版或者類似的一些版本
We'll just use whatever the currently published Xcode is.
我們只用當前最新的 Xcode
Okay.
So, I'm going to start this demo actually by launching Xcode.
那麼我要開始運行 Xcode 來演示了
So, here it is, right here. Xcode.
在這 Xcode
And when you launch Xcode, let's hide others here.
運行 Xcode 以後，我們把其他東西隱藏起來
You're gonna get this splash screen and
你會看到這個歡迎界面，
on this splash screen on the right, this is gonna be all your projects.
在歡迎界面的右邊，將顯示你所有的項目
Now, since it's the beginning of the quarter, we don't have any projects yet,
由於這是本學期開始，我們還沒有任何項目
but they'll all be listed here, so as the quarter goes by this will fill up.
但是慢慢的，我們會逐漸將這個列表填滿
You can turn this splash screen off, if you don't like it by the way.
如果你不喜歡這個歡迎頁面，可以將它關閉
This splash screen also lets us do things like playgrounds and
歡迎界面中也可以創建例如 playground，
a source code management right down here.
或者源代碼管理，在這裡
We're not gonna be doing that for a while.
我們在很長一段時間內不會碰那些
We're gonna be focusing on this option, right here.
我們需要關注的是這個選項，這裡
Create a new Xcode project.
創建一個新的 Xcode 項目
If you don't have the splash screen, you can go to File > New > Project. Kay.
如果你看不到歡迎界面，你也可以 File > New > Project
Same thing, those both the same thing.
它們都是一樣的
So I'm gonna click right here on Create a new project.
下面我點擊這裡，創建一個新項目
When I create a new project, it wants to know what kind of project you want to create,
當我創建新項目的時候，它需要知道你想創建什麼類型的項目
because Xcode is actually used on Mac OS X and to build frameworks and all that stuff.
Xcode 可以被用於在 Mac OS X 上創建框架，以及所有類似的東西
But we're always gonna be building iOS Applications.
但是我們將要創建的是 iOS 應用
And in fact, we're always gonna use this template right here,
事實上，我們經常用到這裡的模板，
Single View Application.'Kay?
Single View Application
That's kind of your basic MVC starter application and
這就是你的基礎 MVC 入門應用
we're gonna build very complicated apps out of that, but we're gonna start here,
我們會用其他這些創建非常複雜的應用，但是我們從這裡開始
so you always click on that one.
所以你會經常點這個
Then it wants to know what you want to call your app, and
你需要填寫應用的名稱，
we're building a calculator, so we're gonna call our app, Calculator.'Kay?
我們在創建的是計算器應用，所以我們給它起名為，Calculator
This organization name doesn't really matter that's just gonna appear in
orgnization 並不重要，它只會出現在
copyright notice and the code that you write at the top in a comment so
類似版權信息，或者你的代碼開頭的注釋中，所以
don't worry about that.
不用管它
But this organization identifier that is very important.
但是這裡的 organization Identifier 是非常重要的
'Kay, this uniquely identifies you. Okay?
它是你的唯一標識符
So that on the next line we can you just,
所以在下一行裡，我們需要一個新的
new uniquely idefy, identify your calculator.
唯一的標識符，標識你的計算器
So here if your a Stanford student,
所以如果你是史丹佛的學生，
you'll wanna use this reverse DNS notation here edu.stanford.cs193p.
你可以用這個倒序的域名：edu.stanford.cs193p
And instead of instructor there, you wanna put your SU net ID.'Kay?
並用你的 SU net ID 將 instructor 替換
Cuz nobody else has that but you.
因為你的 ID 不會和別人的重復
And that'll uniquely identify you.
這樣這個標識符就能作為唯一標識你
As I said, we're using Swift not Objective-C.
我說過，我們要用 Swift 而不是 Objective-C
And we're gonna build an app that works be, equally well on iPad and iPhone,
我們要創建的應用要能同時工作在 iPad 和 iPhone 上，
that's called a universal app.
所以選擇 Universal
You can pick to develop for only one or the other.
你也可以選擇只為其中一種設備開發
But we are going to go Universal here.
但是我們在這裡選擇 Universal
We're not gonna really be doing the iPad part of it for a couple weeks.
在這幾周之內我們不會做這個應用的 iPad 部分
But it is our intent to eventually build an app that works on both.
但是我們最終會把它設計成一個同時能夠運行在 iPad 和 iPhone 上的應用
Okay we're not going to be using Core Data,
我們現在還用不到 Core Data
that's object oriented database stuff so you just leave that unchecked.
那是面向對象的數據庫，現在先不選它
And now it's asking where we want to save it, I strongly recommend saving in your
現在，它問我們要把項目保存在哪裡，我強烈建議保存在你的
home directory, this is my home directory here in a folder called Developer, okay?
home 目錄下，這是我的 home 目錄，裡面有一個 Developer 的目錄，看到沒？
You could put other folders in here if you want to arrange it more,
當然你也可以在這裡放其它文件夾，如果你想創建更多的話
but home directory Developer, I highly recommend that.
不過我建議你放在主目錄下的 Developer 文件夾
Source Control, we will be talking about that at some point in the quarter but
Source Control，我們將會在這學期的某些時候講到，不過
we're not gonna do it right off the bat here so
我們先跳過這個
you can leave that unchecked as well.
所以那個選項你可以不打勾
All right, so here's our first project, its been created so
好，這就是我們創建的第一個項目
this is Xcode that your seeing right here, this is Xcode's main screen and
這裡你看到的就是 Xcode, 這是 Xcode 的主窗口
the center is really what your working on.
中間這部分是主要的工作區域
The left is, area here, is called the navigator, and the navigator you,
左邊的區域，被稱作 Navigator（導航欄）
you use to kind of choose what you're working on but you can also do
通常用來選擇特定的選項，不過也你可以
things over here like search hough your whole project, that's this little guy.
點擊這個小圖標，對整個項目進行搜索
Look at all your break points maybe, look at previous builds that you've done,
這裡用來查看斷點，這裡用來查看之前編譯的項目
browse your project by class hierarchy, all that stuff.
這裡可以以類的層次結構展開整個項目，等等
But we're usually on the left most one here which is just all of the files in
不過我們通常會點擊最左邊的這裡，這裡可以看到我們所有的文件
your project which can also can be organized hierarchically like this.
你的項目可以像這樣按層次的展現出來
And when you select something here on the left,
當你選擇左邊區域這裡的某些部分，
the middle will fill up with what that you've selected so.
中間區域會出現你剛剛選擇的那部分內容
Here I have the actual project itself selected.
這裡我選擇了這個項目本身
So these are the project settings of which there are tons.
所以這裡可以看到這個項目的很多設置項
All along the top here you can see tons of settings.
在這上面你還可以看到更多設置項
We're, we'll go through them as the quarter goes on and
隨著學期進展我們將會講到這些
you've already seen some of them like the bundle identifier there and
你已經看到其中的一部分，比如這裡的 Bundle identifier（包標識符）
the fact this is a universal app.
還可以看到這裡是一個通用 app
We're not going to talk about anymore of this today,
不過我們今天不會講關於項目設置
this project settings business.
的更多內容
We're gonna focus here on some of these files.
我們會把注意力集中在這些文件
And even some of these files, like this AppDelegate,
甚至是這些文件，比如 AppDelegate
I'm just gonna move that down to Supporting Files to get it out of the way.
我會把它們移到 Supporting Files
Same things with these image assets,
image assets 文件夾也是
LaunchScreen well get to this later in the quarter.
LaunchScreen 我們之後會講到
But I wanna focus on these two files right here.
不過我們現在會把注意力集中在這兩個文件上
Okay Main.storyboard and ViewController.swift, okay
Main.storyboard 和 ViewController.swift
In the MVC world by the way, this is the V,
順便說，在 MVC 中這稱為 V
the view and this is the C, the controller but we will talk about MVC on Wednesday.
即視圖，這是 C，即控制器，我們將在週三講到 MVC
So what do these things contain?
所以，這些東西包含什麼
So this Main.storyboard, if I click on it,
這是 Main.storyboard，如果我點擊它
you see it appear in the middle, this is our UI.
可以看到我們的 UI 出現在中間
Okay, this is our user interface.
這就是我們的 UI
So for a calculator this is going to be a little display,
對於計算器而言，這裡將會是一個稍微小一點的顯示區域
this shows the number that we're working on or whatever at the top.
這裡會顯示我們計算出來的數字或任何其它在上面的數字
And lots of buttons down here, number buttons, times, multi, or sorry, times,
下面這裡會有很多按鈕，包括數字，乘除
divide, plus, minus, square root.
加減，平方根
That's all going to be here.
都會出現在這裡
So we're going to build this entire user interface.
所以我們完全使用圖形化來搭建
Purely graphically.
整個用戶界面
Okay? We're not gonna be writing code.
我們不會寫代碼
Put button at this location.
來指出哪個按鈕該放哪個位置
None of that, okay?
一點代碼都沒有
We just literally with our mouse are gonna build this whole user interface.
我們只是用我們的鼠標來搭建我們的用戶界面
So what's the code, what do we need any code for?
那我們的代碼寫在哪裡，什麼時候需要寫代碼？
Well, we, this ViewController.swift, this is a Swift file.
看 ViewController.swift，這個 Swift 文件
This is your first look at Swift for most of you.
這是你們中多數人第一次看 Swift 文件
This controller is gonna control that user interface.
這是我們的 controller，用來控制我們的用戶界面
That's why we call it the view controller or the controller.
這就是為什麼我們稱之為 view controller 或 controller
It controls user interface and that means it's gonna do things that
它控制 UI，這意味著它會做某些事情來
are specific to how this user interface, a calculator's user interface, works.
比如指定這個 UI，計算器界面應該怎樣工作
So when we press the digit buttons, it's going to have update the display.
這樣當你點擊數字按鈕，它會更新顯示的內容
When we press times, it's gonna have to do some multiplication and
當我們點擊乘法，它將會進行乘法運算並且
then put the result in the display.
把結果顯示出來
So it's controlling the display.
所以說它會控制界面的展示
Okay so we'll get back to this code in a moment but we're gonna start by
我們稍後再回到這裡，現在我們先從搭建界面開始
building our user interface and by the way, your user interface, you can see I
順便說一句，你可以看到這個用戶界面
have a low resolution screen here so my UI doesn't even really fit in the space here.
因為屏幕的低分辨率，所以我的 UI 沒有很好地適應空間
You'll probably have maybe a little higher resolution screen then I do but
你們可能有比我更高的屏幕分辨率的屏幕
if you don't, you can zoom in and out, I'm just right-clicking,
不過如果你們沒有，你們可以通過右鍵點擊來進行放大和縮小
if you right-click on the background area here, you can zoom in and out.
如果你在這個背景區域點擊右鍵，你可以放大縮小
You can also do it by double-clicking so if I double-click on this,
你也可以採用雙擊，看如果我雙擊這裡
it zooms it to normal, if I double-click on the background, it zooms out so
它放大到正常水平，如果我再雙擊背景，它會縮小
that way I can see my whole UI.
這樣我可以看到我的整個 UI 界面
Now when we build a complicated app
當我們完成了一個複雜的 app
we're gonna have a whole bunch of these little square areas, we call these scenes,
我們將會有一大堆這些方塊區域，這些我們稱之為 scenes（場景）
and a scene represents kind of phone full, phone screen full of information.
一個場景代表一個完整顯示所有信息的手機屏幕
Okay and as you you've used many iOS applications, you know that you
就像你使用過的許多 iOS 程序
transition from one screen to another as the user goes through the app and
你知道用戶使用這個 app 從一個屏幕切換到另外一個屏幕
that's how your gonna build your apps as well.
這也是你搭建 app 的方式
And this StoryBoard is eventually gonna have a big map showing all
這個 StoryBoard 最終將會有一個大的圖來顯示所有的
the transitions between all those scenes.
場景間的切換
Okay, so this StoryBoard is gonna get big for
好了，所以這個 StoryBoard 將會用來搭建
big apps, your really gonna see your whole application which is kinda cool.
完整的 app，所以當你真的看到整個應用程序時，還挺 cool 的
So we're gonna start small though, just this one little screen right here.
所以我們將從這一個小的場景開始
Which is gonna be our calculator.
搭建我們的計算器
So let's start building our calculator with it's display.
我們先從搭建計算器的界面顯示開始
So I wanna make a display.
當我想顯示一些東西時，
So how do I do that?
我應該怎麼做呢？
Well that brings us to the right side, the right-hand side here,
我們看一下這裡的右邊區域
this whole right side, this is called the Utilities area
右邊的整塊區域，我們稱為 Utilities （工具）區域
You can see that's it's got a bottom and a top, right?
你可以看到這裡有底部和頂部，對不？
We want to go into the bottom and on the third tab right here, which is called
來到底部這裡的第三個按鈕，它被我們稱為
the Object Library, you'll see that there's tons and tons of objects in here.
Object Library （對象庫），你可你看到這裡有非常多的對象
Okay, dozens of these things and
非常多的這類東西
we're gonna get to a lot of these by the end of the quarter.
我們整個學期會接觸到很多這樣的東西
But these are the things you build your user interface out of.
這些是用於搭建你的 UI 的
So kind of towards the top, not all the way at the top, but towards the top,
靠近上面，但不完全靠近上面，就在這上面
you'll start seeing things like buttons and text fields and things like that.
你會開始看到像按鈕，文本區域這樣的東西
Well this is what we need obviously, to build our display here,
很明顯這是我們構建顯示區域所需要的東西
is some sort of text field, and there's a couple of them here.
是某種顯示文本的區域，這裡有兩種
One, this one called Label is static text, you see?
這一種稱為 Label 的是一種靜態的文本
And this one Text Field is editable text, in other words you can touch on this one.
這種稱為 Text Field 是可編輯的文本，也就是說，你當你按下時
And the little keyboard would slide up from the bottom and you could type in it.
鍵盤會從底部滑出來，所以你可以輸入文本
So, the calculator, you can't really touch on the screen and start typing
因此對於計算器來說，你確實不能按下屏幕並且輸入，
so we want this static text.
所以我們需要靜態的文本
So, I'm just going to pick this up with the mouse and drag it out.
所以我用鼠標把它拖出來
Now, when I drag it out into my UI,
現在，當我把它拖入我的 UI 中時
you're going to see a lot of little blue dash lines appearing.
你會看到很多藍色虛線出現
You see these?
看到沒？
These are helping me put this in the right place.
這些可以幫助我們正確地擺放這些東西
So, I can put it right in the center, for example, of my view.
比如說我可以把它放在視圖的中間
I could put it up in a corner up here, which is what I'm gonna do.
我可以把它放在靠頂部這裡，我待會就準備這樣做
Mm-kay.
You always want your things that you put in your UI,
你總是會希望你放入 UI 中的東西
as much as humanly possible, to be on one of these dashed blue lines.
盡可能地去利用這些藍色虛線
And you'll understand why in a couple weeks when we starting talking about Auto Layout.
當你後面學習到 Auto Layout (自動佈局) 時就會明白為什麼這麼做了
I'm gonna do a little Auto Layout right here just to kind of
我這裡將會涉及一點關於 Auto Layout 的東西，可以讓你
give you a feel for it.
對它有點感覺
But those blue, dashed blue lines are gonna be your best friend when it comes to
不過，在你搭建用戶界面的時候，這些藍色虛線將會給你最大的幫助
building your user interface and you'll quickly see why that is.
你會很快知道為什麼了
Once you drag something out like this, you can,
每次你像這樣拖動東西，你可以
these little things are rounded that show it's selected, right?
看到環繞在外面的東西，它表明瞭這個被選中了
They also are little resize handles so you can grab them and resize them.
它們也可以用於調整大小，所以可以抓住它然後或者重新調整它們的大小
When you resize it also re-puts those dashed blue lines out there, okay?
當你調整大小時，這些藍色虛線會重新排成一列，看到沒？
So you definitely wanna, even have,
所以當你調整大小時，你肯定想
when you're resizing, get those things lining up.
把這些東西排成一列
You can also manipulate it directly, just double-click on it.
你還可以直接編輯它，只需要雙擊一下
like a calculator probably doesn't want to come up, this is gonna be initial state of this.
通常計算器的初始狀態不是這樣子
Doesn't want to come up saying Label, it probably wants 0 or
初始狀態上面不會顯示 Label，它可能會顯示 0
something like that in it's display.
或類似的東西
There's also things you wanna set about this though or
另外還有一種，當你無法直接編輯這些
anything you drag in your UI that you just can't direct manipulate and
你拖到 UI 里的內容時，
that's what the top half of this Utilities windows is, is for, okay?
你可以使用右上方的 Utilities windows（工具窗口）
So if you look at the top half here,
所以當你看上面這裡，
there's a bunch of tabs across the top including something like this,
在頂部這裡有許多標籤，包括像這種
the Size Inspector for setting the size of this thing.
用於設置尺寸的 Size Inspector（尺寸檢查器）
And this tab right here, really important, this is the Attributes Inspector.
這個標籤，稱作 Attributes Inspector（屬性檢查器），非常重要
And this is an object oriented inspector, depending on what you have selected.
這是一個面向對象的檢查器，當你選擇不同的東西時
You'll have different user interface here in the top.
用戶界面將會有所改變
And this let's you edit attributes about what's selected.
通過它可以讓你修改選中的內容的屬性
So, for example,
比如
a calculator, the zero doesn't really want to be on the left, right?
計算器中這個 0 其實不是在左邊，對不？
Calculators, the zero, the numbers are on the right and
這個 0 應該是在右邊
they kind of grow out from the right.
這些數字就像是從右邊出現的
And so we can easily fix that with this Alignment thing right here.
我們可以很輕鬆地使用這裡的 Alignment（校准）修改它
So I'm gonna click this and you see the zero move over to the right.
我點擊這裡，你就可以看到 0 到了右邊
And, and maybe I want a bigger font.
還有，也許我想要大點的字體
You see the Font right here.
你可以看到這裡的 Font（字體）
I can click on this, pick different fonts.
我可以點擊這裡，選擇不同的字體
I'm gonna just move it up to like 32 point, it's a nice big font.
把它增大到 32 點，稍微大點的字體
You can notice it kinda cuts off.
你可以看到內容有點被裁剪了
I made it so big that it's too small.
字體放大後，因此這裡顯得太小
So I can always just resize this larger to make that fit.
所以我可以重新調整大小，使它能夠適應字體的大小
So this is how we build our user interface.
這就是我們搭建用戶界面的方式
It's very direct manipulation and very object oriented as you'll start to
非常直觀的操作，並且非常地面向對象
see when we add different kinds of objects.
當你加入不同的對象時你就可以看到
So, let's actually run this application, okay?
所以，讓我們真正地運行我們的應用吧
We haven't done, built any calculaterness about it,
儘管我們還沒有完成任何關於計算的東西，
but we have this one field, let's run it and see what it looks like.
不過可以讓我們運行一下看看是什麼效果
So, how do you run things?
應該怎麼運行？
Well, you see right here where it says, iPhone 6?
嗯，這裡你可以看到，iPhone 6？
This actually is a selector that lets you say where you want to
這實際上是可以讓你選擇用什麼設備
run your application.
運行你的應用
So you can see you can run it on an iOS device if you have one connected,
如果當你連上了一個 iOS 設備時，你可以在 iOS 設備上運行，
I don't have one connected currently.
現在我還沒有連接
But you can do that.
不過你可以這樣做試試
And we'll talk in a Friday section probably in a week or
我們將會在一到兩周後的週五的課上
two about how to get your devices hooked up.
談論如何連接你的設備
But also there's these plethora of simulators here, iPhone 6,
不過這裡有很多模擬器， iPhone 6 、
6+, iPhone 5, iPhone 4s, iPad Airs.
6+、 iPhone 5、 iPhone 4s、 iPad Airs
And you can pick one of these to run on and
你可以選擇其中的一個運行，
it'll actually simulate that device right here on your computer.
它們實際上是在你的電腦上模擬那些設備
So I'm gonna run on the iPhone 6.
這裡我將會運行在 iPhone 6 上
Okay,I'm just gonna hit Play, see this Play button right here?
好了，我將要點擊 Play 按鈕，看到 Play 按鈕沒？
That's how you simulate, so Play.
這就是使用模擬器的方式，點擊 Play
Now it's launching the simulator.
現在啓動模擬器
It's a separate process.
它是一個單獨的程序
And it's going to run our App in there.
我們的 App 將會運行在它裡面
And there it is.
就是這樣
Now you might say, whoop.
現在你可能會說，哇！
Big white square.
這麼大的白色正方形
Oh that's not so good.
看起來不怎麼好
And the reason this is so
這是因為
big is because the iPhone 6 has a very high resolution display on it.
iPhone 6 的高分辨率屏幕
Okay, the retina display, and it's way higher resolution than my computer, okay?
這種視網膜屏幕，比我電腦上的分辨率大得多，對吧？
So I actually have to scroll around, you see there's the top of it.
所以我不得不上下滾動，你可以看到它的頂部
Scroll up and down to get to it all.
通過上下滾動可以看到整個區域
Luckily if you go to Window, this is not in the simulator now, the iOS simulator.
如果我們前往 Window 選項，這個選項現在不在 iOS 模擬器
If you go to Window and Scale, you can scale it down to be smaller and
如果你點擊 Window 並且點擊 Scale， 你可以把它縮小，
then it'll fit.
然後它的大小就與屏幕的大小匹配了
Okay, so if you have a low resolution screen,
因此，如果你有低分辨率的屏幕
you're definitely gonna wanna use Window > Scale.
你可以點擊 Window > Scale
Cmd+3 right there is another way to do it.
也可以實用快捷鍵 Cmd+3
Okay?
懂不？
So here's our UI, but it doesn't look to good, okay, because where's this?
這就是我們的 UI，不過看起來不怎麼樣，因為這些在哪裡？
We put this zero in there and it just never showed up, what did we do wrong?
我們把 0 放在那裡，卻從來都沒有出現，我們哪裡做錯了？
Well we didn't really do anything wrong and that zero is actually there.
實際上我們沒有做錯，那個 0 實際上就在那裡
It's just here. Let me line up these UI's, this is not
就在那，先讓我把它們排成一列，雖然沒有
necessarily exactly the same scale but its appropriate, approximately the same scale,
完全相同的比例但也是近似的，近似相同的比例，
you can see that the zero is actually off screen, [NOISE] okay?
你可以看到那個 0 實際上在屏幕外面，看到不？
So its there but you just can't see it because its over here off the screen.
所以實際上它存在不過你看不到它，因為它在屏幕外面
Okay, and that's a problem, but that's a problem we can fix.
這是一個問題，不過這個問題我們可以解決
So let's go fix that problem.
來，我們開始解決這個問題吧
Why is that thing off-screen?
為什麼它在屏幕外面？
Well, look at this UI right here, okay?
好了，看到這個 UI 沒？
What shape is it?
它是什麼形狀的？
It's square.
它是正方形的
Okay, no iOS device is square.
不過沒有任何 iOS 設備是正方形的
There's not a single square iOS device in the world.
世界上沒有任何一種正方形的 iOS 設備
They're all, you know, tall and thin,
你知道的，它們都是高的，並且瘦的，
or, if you turn them sideways, then they're long and short.
或者如果把它們側身來看，它們都又長又短
Or even like an iPad.
甚至包括 iPad
You know the aspect ratio on an iPad is slightly different than an iPhone so
你知道 iPad 的縱橫比例和 iPhone 稍微有點不同
their all slightly different, but none of them are square.
它們略有不同，但它們都不是正方形的
So why do we design our UI in a square?
那為什麼我們把 UI 設計為方的？
Because the way you design iOS interfaces, you design them in this square and
因為你這種 iOS 界面的設計，是將內容放這個方形中
you give everything inside the square rules, called constraints,
然後給所有的內容都添加規則，這些規則我們稱之為約束，
about what happens to them when they get squished down.
是關於當它們被壓扁時應該發生什麼變化
Either squished down vertically, squished down horizontally,
不過是水平還是垂直的壓扁
depending on what kinda device their getting put on, okay?
取決於它們被放到哪種設備中，明白不？
So you put these rules in there, so, what does it look like to put these rules in?
所以你會在這裡加入這些規則，那當加入這樣規則後會怎樣？
Well again, it's all direct manipulation
同樣的，這些都是直觀的操作
So I'm going to give some rules to this label right here to make it so that it knows
我將要對這裡的這個 Label 增加一些規則，使得它知道
what to do when this square gets squished down in any direction for any device.
對於任何方向的任何設備被壓扁時應該如何顯示
So, what do I want the rules to be?
那我希望這些規則是什麼樣的？
Well, I always want this thing to use the whole width.
我總希望它可以使用全部的寬度
However much width I have, I want it all.
不管我的寬度是多少，我都希望填滿這個寬度
So I'm gonna pin this right edge to this edge, okay?
所以我要固定這個右邊緣到這個邊緣的距離，對吧？
I'm gonna make it so all widths are pinned to each other.
我這樣做是因為所有寬度都會由另外一方決定
And I do that with the Ctrl key.
我使用 Ctrl 鍵來完成
I've turned on sticky keys so
我已經開啓粘滯鍵所以
you can see down in the lower left here, it's showing the modifier keys I'm using.
在左下角你可以看到，它顯示了我正使用的按鍵
So right now I'm holding down Ctrl.
現在我按住 Ctrl
And I'm gonna Ctrl+drag from the right edge of this to the container it's in.
我按住 Ctrl，同時從右邊拖動到它的容器的右邊
See how it's showing me what I'm dragged to.
看它是如何展示我正在拖動的過程
So when I drag to this container, it puts a menu up and says,
當我拖到這個容器時，彈出了一個菜單，上面說，
oh, okay, you want some rule between that label's right edge and
好吧，你想在標籤的右邊緣和當前邊緣之間增加一些規則
this thing's edge, what do you want it to be?
你希望是怎麼樣的規則？
Well, I can do a lot of things here.
恩，我可以做很多事情
I could center this label vertically in this container.
我可以使這個標籤垂直居中於這個容器
Up, you know, vertical up and down.
向上，你知道的，垂直向上和向下
I definitely don't want that, I want my label at the top, so I don't want that.
我絕對不希望出現這種情況，我是希望我的 Label 在頂部
I can make it the equal width,
我可以使它的寬度相等，
So I can make this label the same width as the container.
所以我可以使這個 Label 和容器的寬度相同
I don't want that either, cuz I want this little margin there, right?
我也不想那種情況，因為我想設置這個小的邊距，對不對？
But look at the top one, trailing space to container margin.
不過看上面的那個，trailing space to container margin（距離容器的右間距）
This lets me pin the trailing space after my label to the margin of the container.
這讓我規定了我的 Label 尾部與它的容器的間距
So that's the one I want, so I'm gonna click on this and it does it.
這就時我需要的，我點擊這個來完成
Now, see all these yellow and orange lines that appeared when I did that?
現在，當我這樣做後，看到這些黃色和橙色的線條出現沒？
That's because the systems like, okay, you've started telling me the rules for this label,
這就像是系統在說，嗯，
你已經開始告訴我應該遵循對這個標籤的某些規則，
but your you haven't told me enough rules,
不過你沒有告訴我足夠多的規則
I don't know what to do with this thing.
我不知道應該對它怎麼做，
So now it's showing you all the places where it's like the system's not
所以現在提示你，當它被擠壓的時候
sure what to do now when this thing gets squished.
系統不確定應該怎麼做
Before it was like, okay, well you weren't telling me anything so
在這之前，你沒有告訴我任何規則
I'm not going to do anything, but now your starting to tell me.
所以我沒有顯示任何東西，不過現在你開始告訴我
So what do I do?
所以我應該怎麼做？
So we have to fully specify both the what happens horizontally and
所以我們不得不完整地告訴它水平方向
vertically to this thing.
和垂直方向應該怎麼顯示
So we've only just started here.
所以我們只是先從這裡開始
So let's pin this edge also cuz we want this edge to stay on this side.
讓我們拖動固定這個邊緣，我們希望這個邊緣靠近這一邊
So I'm gonna hold down Ctrl and drag.
所以我按下 Ctrl 並且拖動
And now I'm gonna pin the leading space to the container margin.
然後現在我想固定 Label 前部到容器之間的間距
Okay, boom that did that.
好了，我成功了
Still have orange going on here, that's because I haven't specified anything about
這裡仍然顯示橙色，這是因為我還沒指定任何關於
the vertical position of this label so I'm gonna pin the top to the top, so
這個 Label 的垂直方向的規則，所以我把 Label 的頂部和容器頂部間距固定起來，
hold Ctrl again, drag up here, this is now top space.
所以我又一次按住 Ctrl，拖到這裡，這是頂部間距
Notice that it realizes where I am dragging to and from, right?
注意到它識別出我正把它拖向哪裡沒？
So they can give me options that make sense,
所以它能給我有意義的選項，
like Top Space to Layout Guide here.
比如這裡的 Top Space to Layout Guide(頂部間距)
So I'm going to do that.
所以我會選這個
So now I'm starting to get blue lines.
所以我開始看到藍色的線了
You see these lines?
看到沒？
I hope you can see that there.
希望你能看到
They're solid blue, not orange or red.
它們是實心藍線，不是橙色或紅色
Okay, that's because they're okay, we are okay horizontally here.
這是因為它們可以了，水平方向上沒問題了
But we still have a problem vertically.
不過這裡仍然有一個垂直方向上的問題
Now I'm not sure exactly what the problem is vertically cuz I really don't
現在我不是非常確定這個垂直方向上的問題因為我確實不
want the bottom of this.
希望這樣的底部
I just want it to hang out wherever it wants to hang out based on the size of my
我只是希望這個剛剛擺放的 Label 的底部是基於我的
font or whatever.
字體大小之類的
So I don't, I don't really wanna specify anything here so
因此，我確實不想在這裡指明特定的高度
why is this orange and how do I get rid of this?
所以為什麼橙色警告會出現，我應該怎樣避免它？
Well any time you have orange and when you're doing this layout stuff and
任何時候當你在佈局時看到橙色警告
you don't know what to do.
你不知道應該怎樣做的時候
You wanna go down to this button right here, okay?
你可以點擊下面的這個按鈕，看到不？
This is the document outline.
這是 document outline(文檔大綱)
And when you click this, a little thing will slide out, a little shelf here.
當你點擊這裡時，這部分會滑出來，一個小架子
And this is an outline view of everything that's in your UI.
這是你的 UI 中所有內容的大綱
Okay? And they're linked,
並且它們之間是相互關聯的，
So if I click the background, nothing is selected.
如果我點擊背景，沒有選中任何內容
Then the background, the view is what's selected here.
然後這個背景，這個視圖就是我這裡選擇的
But if I click this L0, which means a label with zero in it,
但當我點擊這裡 L0 標籤時，L0 指的是 Label 中顯示內容是 0，
look it's selected my Zero label,
看我被選中的 Label，
And vice versa if I click on this here, it selects it over here.
選中，反之亦然如果我點擊這裡，這裡顯示被選中
So this is this same thing in an outline mode.
所以這和大綱模式一樣
This is really nice to have.
這是一種非常好的方式
Sometimes you have views that are overlapping and they're kind of in
有時候你的視圖重疊在一起，所以它們顯得有點
each other's way, you can always go here to select the one you want, okay?
難以選擇，你可以來到這裡選擇你想選擇的視圖
And you can Ctrl+drag to these over here too it's just as much Ctrl+draggable as
並且你也可以在這裡 Ctrl + 拖動，這裡和其它東西
some of these other things.
一樣可 Ctrl + 拖動
But what we're, and we'll look,
但這些我們將會
We'll talk about top layout guide, bottom layout guide a little later.
我們將討論一下頂部和底部的佈局指南
But what I really want you to focus on is this little yellow circle up here.
但是我想讓你注意這個黃色的小圓圈
'Kay? Any time you got yellow and
好的，任何時候，你在使用 Auto-layout 中
orange problems with this auto-layout business,
看到黃色和橙色的線
you're gonna get this little yellow circle appearing in your document outline.
你可以在你的 document outline 中看到這個小黃圈
And if you click it, it'll slide in a list of all the problems.
如果你點擊它，它會滑入一個列表，列出所有的問題
And so here I highlight over this and this is where all the orange and yellow is.
如果選中它，出現高亮的部分就是警告所出現的地方
It's saying the label with the 0 in it expected the height to be 39 but
它提示這個顯示 0 的 label 的高度應該是 39，但
the actual height is 57.
真實的情況卻是 57
Well that's because after I set this font,
這是因為我在設置了這個字體後，
I just dragged this down a little bit to make space.
我向下的拖動了一部分，讓它多出來一些空間
All right, I, I wasn't very, I, I didn't know it was supposed to be 39.
我不是很清楚它的高度是否應該 39
I just dragged down.
我只是稍稍向下拖動了而已
And so it's saying that's wrong.
這樣，Xcode 給了我一個警告
Now, I could just try drag it back up and meet this dashed line.
現在，我可以試著將其拖動，和這個虛線重疊
This dashed line, by the way,
強調下這條虛線，
is where it's kind of saying, this is really where this thing wants to be.
它好像就在表明，這個東西想要出現在這裡
But the solid lines are where it actually is.
但是實線是它真實存在的地方
So I could kinda drag it up to there, but I, I could be off by a pixel or something else.
所以我可以把它拖動到那裡，但是我也許會相差 1 個像素或有些其它差別
A much more reliable way is to click this little yellow triangle, 'kay?
現在有一個可靠的方法，點擊這個黃色小三角
So I'm gonna click this yellow triangle.
我將要點擊這個
It's gonna bring up this pop-up window.
它會彈出一個窗口
And there's three ways to fix the problems, okay?
這裡給出了三個修改問題的方法
One way, Update Constraints, this middle way right here.
其中一個，Update Constraints，在中間
That's a way that says, hey, I want this thing to be,
這個方法是，我想要這樣做
this label to be right where it is.
我想讓這個 label 出現在它該出現的位置
So just make some constraints.
所以只要做一些約束
Make it up.
彌補上這個缺點
Make it happen!
發生吧！
And it'll put some wacky constraints in there like 52 high, which is a bad
它會添加一些古怪的約束，例如把高度設置為 52
constraint for it to be, 52 high, cuz this label wants to be its natural height.
這不是我想要的約束，因為 52 的高度不是這個 label 本來的高度
It doesn't want to be 52 high.
它的不想變成 52 這麼高
So this'll kinda force constraint.
所以這裡就像是強制性的約束
You'll almost never want this one, 'kay.
你幾乎永遠不會用到這一項
Rarely do you wanna force the constraints.
你很少需要強制性地去約束
Reset to Suggested Constraints would probably just work here.
Reset to Suggested Constraints 也許會在這裡起作用
I'm not gonna choose this one, but it would probably work.
我不會選擇這個，但是它可能會起作用
This one is going to make the constraints match the blue lines.
這個可以把 label 的約束與藍線重合
Those dashed blue lines that I told you always wanna meet.
我告訴過你那些藍線，是需要必須重疊的
Those are what's gonna help the system pick suggested constraints.
那些是能夠幫助系統選擇建議的約束
So since we dragged that label out to the blue lines perfectly,
如果我們把 label 拖動到藍線的位置
I'll bet if I said Reset to Suggested Constraints, it might just work.
Reset to Suggested Constraints 也是會起作用的
Okay. But I'm actually gonna show you this
但是我想給你們展示頂部的這一項
last option up on top, which is Update Frame and what this says is, take into
Update Frame，這個能夠根據已經設定的約束，
consideration all the rules and move this label to where the rules say it should be.
把 label 移動到該放置的位置
'Kay.And I like this option a lot because it
我比較喜歡這個選項
lets you kind of preview, do I have my little rules right, okay?
它讓你能夠預覽，我的約束是否設置正確了
So let's try that, let's see if the, we'll tell the, move this label, go ahead and
我們嘗試一下，label 是否能夠按照已有的約束，移動到
move yourself and size yourself to obey these three rules we you put in, and
它該去的地方並且設置好自己應有的大小
we'll fix the misplacement, so let's try it.
我們點擊這個按鈕，讓我們嘗試下
And sure enough it did it, it says there are no Auto Layout issues.
果然做到了，沒有任何問題
If I go back to my document outline, this little yellow circle is gone.
如果回到 document outline，這個黃色的小圓圈已經消失了
If I look in my view, everything is blue-lined, no yellow or red.
看看自己的視圖，全部都是藍線，沒有紅色或黃色的
Okay? So that's your
好了嗎？這就說明你的
crash course on Auto Layout, and we're gonna talk a lot more about Auto Layout,
Auto Layout 已經完成，我們接下來討論更多 Auto Layout
in fact, even on Wednesday I'm gonna do another Auto Layout with all the buttons.
在週三的課上，我會對所有的按鈕做一下 Auto Layout
Right? The keypad buttons, and
計算器的所有按鈕
all that, which is a lot more things being laid out.
這聽起來真的蠻多的
But let's see if this fixes our problem.
看看是否修復了問題
Let's go ahead and run our application again.
我們再次運行一下應用
So I'm just hitting that play button.
點擊這個運行按鈕
Here it, oh, we got our zero this time.
此刻，我們可以看到這個 0 了
You see how it pinned this zero to that edge?
你注意到這個 0 固定在邊緣了嗎?
And not only that, if we rotate this phoned,
不僅可以這樣，如果我們旋轉模擬器，
which you can do in the Simulators menu, Hardware > Rotate.
你可以在模擬器的菜單中點擊 Hardware > Rotate
Look the 0, this got wider and the 0 kept pin, pinning itself over to that.
看看這個 0，它變得更寬，0 還是把自己固定在邊緣
And it also stayed on the top even though this got, whole thing got shorter.
它也保持著距離頂部的距離，即使它變窄了一些
Okay. And if I rotate back, the 0 stays there.
接下來，如果我旋轉回來，0 還是保持原樣
Question. So what did it do at the bottom there?
學生提問：底部發生了什麼？
Like what did the actual update frame end up doing?
Update Frame 到底做了什麼事情？
What did the update frame in the document outline do?
Document Outline 中的 Update Frame 到底做了什麼事情？
Yes. It moved this bottom edge up.
它移動了底部的邊緣
You see this is only 39 pixels high now.
你看現在是 39 的像素高度
It was 52.
之前它是 52
So, yeah, it just moved it up.
這樣，它發生了改變，向上移動了
It, it, and if other things had been yellow,
如果還有其他部分有黃色線，
it could have moved the whole thing.
它可能就會移動整個 label
Right? It would move that
好的，它將移動這個 label
whole rectangle wherever the rule said but
來實現約束但是
in this case, you can fix that one problem by moving it up.
這種情況，你可以通過向上拖動來修復這個問題
Good question.
問得不錯
Okay? So that's good.
還不錯
All right.
So that's it for Auto Layout.
這就是 Auto Layout
Auto Layout part one.
Auto Layout 第一部分
So now let's talk a little bit about connecting our user interface that we're
現在我們來說一下如何將 UI
building right here, up to the code,
和代碼建立起聯繫
cuz we want that code to be able to talk to the user interface.
因為我們想讓代碼和 UI 進行交流
Otherwise how are we gonna have the number buttons,
否則我們如何能夠使數字按鈕產生的數字
make numbers appear up here in the display?
顯示在頂部的 label 里
Or the times button, give the results of the calculation up here.
或者按下乘法按鈕，就會把結果顯示在這裡
We gotta be able to talk to this.
我們需要這樣的交流
So how do we do that?
但是如何做到呢？
And the answer, first step is, we need to get both this co, this Swift Code,
第一步，我們要把 view 和 controller 中的 Swift 代碼
the controller, and this view on screen at the same time, 'kay?
同時顯示在屏幕上
Cuz we're gonna connect them so we need them on screen at the same time,
因為我們會連接它們，所以我們需要它們同時顯示在屏幕上
and there's a lot of ways to do that, but I'll do the simplest way right here,
我將用最簡單的方式實現這個
which is this little button called the assistant editor, all right?
使用 Assistant Editor 這個按鈕
So I'm gonna click that and look!
我要點了，看看會發生什麼
It put them both on screen at the same time, exactly what I wanted.
它把它們同時放上屏幕，這正是我想要的
Now it's all a little crowded here.
現在這裡有一點擁擠
Even if I expand my view a little bit, it's like it's all smashed in here.
即使我放大整個界面，它看起來還是這麼小
Luckily the navigator and the utilities can also be hidden,
幸運的是 Navigator 和 Utilities 這些都是可以隱藏起來的，
see these buttons up here, these three buttons?
這裡有三個按鈕
This left one, if you click it hides the navigator and
左側這個，如果你點擊它會隱藏 Navigator
this right one if you click it hides utilities, 'kay?
點擊右側這個，會隱藏右側的 Utilities
So now we have both my UI and over here we can still double click to zoom out, but
現在它們都在我們的視線中，我可以雙擊縮放它
the thing is, anytime we're actually connecting our UI to our code or
但是我們在想要連接代碼和 UI 或者
trying to edit anything in here,you need to be zoomed to normal, 'kay?
嘗試去編輯的時候，你需要把縮放比例調到正常
For example if I tried to select if I'm zoomed out and
例如這個，如果我縮小
I try to select this 0 I just can't.
我就不能選中這個 0 了
This is really kind of a bird's eye view just for seeing what your UI looks like.
這個其實只是一個預覽圖模式，讓你看看大體樣子，而不能編輯
If you wanna actually work on it,
如果你想要編輯
you double-click to zoom in on this scene that you're interested in.
雙擊你需要編輯的窗口就可以了
Okay, so here's our Swift code.
這是我們的 Swift 代碼
I'm actually gonna delete these.
我將要刪除這些
We don't need them for the calculator.
在我們的應用中是不需要這些的
We will need these things for future application but we don't need it for the calculator.
我們會在將來的應用需要這些，但在這裡不需要
And this is your first look at Swift, 'kay.
這是你第一次看到 Swift 代碼
So Swift, as I said, very concise language, but it's basically an object
Swift 是非常簡潔的、
oriented language, it's gonna look a lot like C, some things look a lot like Java.
面向對象的語言，它看起來像 C，有些東西像 Java
It's kind of the, you know, best of, of a lot of different worlds at once.
它集眾多語言之長
Now this import is just importing the UI portion of iOS.
這句 import 導入了 iOS 的 UI 部分
You usually won't have to specify import yourself unless you start
除非你需要使用一些框架，
using frameworks that are not, you know, the base frameworks and we'll get to that
通常來說不需要自己導入，我們幾周後會講到那裡
probably weeks into the quarter where you fi, finally have to do an import yourself.
最後你還是得自己導入
So this how it automatically got put here for us.
這裡我們看到它自動的為我們添加了
And so this is really your first line of Swift code, 'kay?
在這是你的第一行 Swift 代碼
Appropriately, it's a definition of a class.
這裡是定義了一個類
Cuz Swift is fundamentally object-oriented and here we're defining a class.
因為 Swift 是以面向對象為基礎的，這裡是定義的一個類
So what does the syntax look like to define a class?
定義一個類的語法是什麼樣的？
You got the keyword class.
你得使用關鍵字 class
You got the name of the class.
這裡是這個類的名稱
Now this name ViewController, pretty bad name,
現在這個名字 ViewController 看起來很糟糕
Okay, very generic, really they should probably be something like
非常普通的名字，它應該起名為例如
CalculatorViewController,something specific to
CalculatorViewController 這樣有針對的名字，
this particular scene that we're orking on right here, that it's controlling.
這樣看起來就讓人清楚它是控制哪裡的了
This is the default name it gives you.
這是個默認的名字
I don't want to spend the valuable demo time showing how to
我不想花費寶貴的時間去演示如何
rename this cuz unfortunately,
重命名，因為
I can't just type a new name here because I gotta keep the UI in sync with it.
我不能在這裡輸入一個新名字, 因為我要保持 UI 與之同步
So I would have to do something in the UI as well.
所以我必須在 UI 中做一些事情
But, for now, for your first assignment or two we're, we'll just
你的第一次或第二次作業，我們只會
call this ViewController, but down the road you're gonna wanna pick better names.
叫它 ViewController，但在這之後，你最好給他更換一個好的名字
And of course you're gonna be building multiple of
當然你將會在這個應用的這個類中
these scenes in this class in the same app in the future, so
創建多個場景
of course, they'll all have different controller names.
當然它們每一個都有不同的 controller 名稱
Okay, this :UIViewController, that's inheritance, that's its superclass, okay?
這個 ':UIViewController' 是告訴我們它的父類是誰
Swift is single inheritance, so you can only inherit from one class.
Swift 是單繼承，你只能讓它繼承一個類
It's perfectly fine in Swift not to inherit from a class if you don't want to, all right?
在 Swift 中，你不想繼承也可以
But here we have to inherit from UIViewController cuz we
但在這裡我們必須繼承於 UIViewController
want all this magic that allows us to control the UI,
想通過它來控制 UI，
like that whole Auto Layout business, and there's a ton of mechanism in here for
像 Auto Layout，這有很多種方式來讓
the, the allowing the controller to control this UI.
controller 控制 UI
So obviously we do that so all ViewControllers, all controllers of these
很明顯，所有 ViewController, 所有這些場景中的 controller
little scenes always inherit from either from UIViewController directly or they
必須直接繼承於 UIViewController，或者繼承於繼承 UIViewController 的子類
inherit from a class that inherits from UIViewController or up their chain so.
或者在繼承鏈條上
And then inside this curly brace is simply all the instance variables and
在這個花括號里是所有的實例變量和
methods in this class, 'kay?
方法
So very simple syntax to define a class.
定義類的語法是非常簡練的
So let's dive right into making some instance variables and methods so
所以讓我們定義一些實例變量和方法
you can see what those look like.
來看看語法是什麼樣的
And I thought we, this was segued to because we're going to
我們要把這個
say we wanted to connect this UI to this code.
這個 UI 對象連接到代碼中
So let's do that.
我們現在就這樣做
Let's connect this label right here into this code, and
我們連接這個 label 到代碼中去，
then we're gonna do that by  making an instance variable.
然後我們會創建一個實例變量
In Swift we call them properties.
在 Swift 中我們叫它們 properties
'Kay so if you hear me say property,
如果你聽到我說 property，
I'm basically talking about an instance variable.
那我其實就是在說實例變量
Right? A variable that is part of the class.
清楚嗎？實例變量是類中的一個變量
Every instance of the class gets its own copy of it.
類的每個實例都有它自己的拷貝
Hopefully you all know what an instance variable is.
希望你們都知道什麼是實例變量
If you don't, again, this class,
如果你不清楚，再說一次，這門課程
heavy object-oriented, you should definitely know that.
需要很強的面向對象功底，你們應當很清楚
So I'm gonna make a property here, an instance variable,
我將要聲明一個 property ，也可以說是一個實例變量
that points to this label, so that I can update the label's text, right?
使用指針指向這個 label，這樣就我就能夠更新這個 label 的內容了
I need to be able to talk to this label, and the way you do that in eh,
我得跟這個 label 通信，方法是
in Xcode is you hold down Ctrl, just like we did when we were making
在 Xcode 中，按住 Ctrl，像剛才和邊緣連接那樣
a connection to the edge, so I'm holding down Ctrl and clicking on the label, but
所以我按住 Ctrl，連接 label
instead of going to the edge, I'm gonna go into the code, 'kay?
但這次是連接到代碼中去
Now this is kinda wacky.
這是有點古怪
I know a lot of you are like what?
我知道你們都會感覺很奇怪
Into the code?
放到代碼里？
Yeah?
So we're going right into the code here and let go and it's gonna say oh,
現在我們到右邊代碼中，松開鼠標
you wanna make a connection between your UI and your controller.
你想連接 UI 和 controller
No problem, what kinda connection you wanna make?
你需要哪種連接？
And we wanna make what's called an outlet connection.
我們需要設置 outlet 連接
An outlet means an instance variable or
outlet 代表指向 UI 的
property that points to this thing in the UI.
實例變量或 property
And all it needs to know to do that is, what do you wanna call this property?
接下來它需要知道 property 應該叫什麼名字
And this is the display of my calculator so I'm gonna call this display and it
它將是我計算器的顯示部分，所以我將它命名為 display，
already knows the type of the thing is UILabel of course cuz we dragged from here.
因為我們是從 label 拽過來的，所以知道它的類型
Don't worry about this weak, I'll talk about that in a moment.
不要擔心這個 weak，在後面我們會講到
And then we just hit Connect, and it creates an instance variable or
然後我們點擊 connect, 它會在 controller 中
property, right here in our controller.
創建一個實例變量或 property
So this is a great opportunity to look at the syntax in Swift for
這是一個很好的機會瞭解，在 Swift 中如何
creating a property.
創建一個 property 的語法
And there's a couple of things on here that are not normally part of it.
這裡有幾件事情通常都不是它的一部分
This is you, the main syntax for creating a property.
這是你創建一個 property 的主要語法
Let's quickly look at this thing to get it out of the way.
我們快速的瞭解下這個用法
This is not really part of the Swift language proper.
這不是 Swift 真正語言的一部分
This is something Xcode puts in here so
這個小圓圈是 Xcode 生成的
that this little circle, do you see the little circle in this gutter, appears?
這個小圓圈出現在這裡，你看到了嗎？
This little circle when I mouse over it, look what Xcode does.
當我把鼠標移動到上面時候，看看 Xcode 的變化
It shows me what this line of code is connected to.
它展示了這行代碼所連接到了什麼地方
'Kay? So that's really cool, and
這看起來非常酷，
you're gonna see that's really valuable later in this demo,
在這個 demo 中，這是非常有用的，
is being able to find out what things are connected to.
它能找到我們連接的是什麼控件
So that's all this thing means here.
這個就是它在這裡所展示的意義
You, you, you don't type this in yourself, that when you Ctrl+drag, it puts it there.
當你按下 Ctrl 同時點擊拖動時候，你（可能）不懂這裡出現的 Weak 的意思
This weak, all you, you, if you come from other languages,
如果你從其他語言過來的
you're used to things like garbage collection to clean up the heap.
你會使用過類似的垃圾回收機制
Or maybe you even have to alloc and
或者你也許在一些語言里習慣
free things yourself manually in some languages.
自己手動管理內存
None of that in Swift.
在 Swift 中是沒有的
In Swift, the, all objects live in the heap, 'kay.
在 Swift 中，所有的對象都在堆中
All class, the instances of classes live in the heap.
所有類，類的實例都存在堆中
And the memory for them is managed for you, 'kay?
而 Swift 已經替你進行了內存管理
You allocate them as much as you want, as soon as there's no pointers to them,
只要沒有了指針指向它們，你可以隨意分配它們內存
they get cleaned up, and it's not garbage collection, 'kay?
它們會自動清理，但不是垃圾回收機制
It's reference counting.
這就是引用計數
It's actually counting references to them but it's all automatic.
它實際上是計算引用它們的次數，但這都是自動的
The only thing you ever have to be maybe interested in is this weak business which
你剛才也許唯一感興趣的是這個 weak 的作用
is less than a hundredth of a percent of the time.
這東西出現的次數不會太頻繁
And for the first four weeks of this class, forget about weak.
前四周的課程中，忘掉這個 weak
It'll automatically happen when you do this Ctrl+drag, but just ignore it.
它會自動在你當你按下 Ctrl 同時拖動時候出現，但是先忽略它
But the main thing to know is that all that memory
而最主要的事情是你要知道內存管理
management is happening for you.
是如何發生的
Also this, instance variable right here,
同時，實例變量在這裡，
which is a pointer to this object, notice there's no ampersands or
它是指向對象的指針，注意這裡沒有與符號 「&」 或者 「*」
stars or any other kind of syntax that says this is a pointer.
或者其他任何語法說這是一個指針
'Kay?
If you have a instance, variable or property or
一個實例，變量或屬性或
local variable that is an object, okay,
局部變量都是一個對象
it's always a pointer to it cuz objects only live in the heap, 'kay?
它總是一個指針，因為對象只在堆中存在著
So you don't need all that extra stars and
所以不需要多餘的 「*」 和 「&」，
ampersand, any of that business from other languages, okay?
或者其他語言中類似作用的東西
This exclamation point, by the way, I'm gonna talk about in a few minutes,
順便說一下這個感嘆號，我要談幾分鐘
has nothing to do with this being an object, okay?
這是和對象不相關的
This is, this totally separate thing.
這完全不相干的事情
We'll get to it.
我們待會就會理解它
All right.
So let's look at this.
所以讓我們看看這個
This is the syntax for defining a property, 'kay?
這個語法定義了一個屬性，對嗎？
An instance variable.
一個實例變量
And it's very simple.
並且它是如此的簡單
You got var, short for variable cuz that's what this is, a variable.
你看到的這個 var，它是變量（variable）的縮寫
The name, this is the name of it, display.
這是變量的名稱：display
Okay? That's just the name of this property.
這個屬性的名字就是這個
And then :UILabel!
緊接著就是 UILabel
Is the type, 'kay?
這個是它的類型
That's the type of this instance variable.
這個是這個實例變量的類型
So again, I'll talk about the exclamation point later, but
我稍後會講到那個感嘆號
obviously this thing is pointing to this label so that we can talk to it.
但很明顯，我們可以確定這個東西是指向 label 的
And we'll be doing that in a moment.
我們待會就能確定
'Kay?
Questions?
有什麼疑問嗎？
All right, let's talk about another kind of connection we may,
好的，讓我們來談談另一種連接，
we can make, let's start putting some buttons in our calculator.
讓我們開始放一些計算器的按鈕吧
So I'm gonna go back to the Utilities window, 'kay?
我將要回到這個 Utilities 窗口
By pressing this button over here,
按下這個按鈕
go down to the bottom, go to the third tab over here, the object library.
找到下方的第三個選項卡的對象目錄
And instead of a label, this time I'm gonna drag out a button.
這次拖的不是 label，我將要拖出來一個按鈕
Okay? I'm gonna put this button here now.
現在我要把這個按鈕放到這裡
Just to be different, I'm not gonna initially line it up with a blue line.
和剛才有點不一樣，沒有初始化藍色的線
I'm just gonna put it kinda in space out here and
我只是想把它放在這個空間中，
I'll line it up with the blue line later, 'kay?
我等下將把它放在藍線的下面
But I don't wanna forget to do that though, I always wanna do that.
希望我待會不會忘記這麼做
What I'm gonna do later is to show you it can be done.
我等下要做的事就是告訴你這是可以做到的
So, this is gonna be, let's say this is gonna be one of our number buttons.
所以，這會是我們其中的一個數字按鈕
Like the upper left corner of our keypad is a 7.
就像鍵盤左上角的數字 7
Okay?
Again, I have the same thing over here.
我還需要其他的一些按鈕
Okay? With the attributes inspector I can
通過 attributes inspector ，我能夠
change things like the font.
對字體什麼的作出修改
Let's make this be 24 point, let's say.
讓我們試著把字號改成 24
I can resize.
我能這麼調整大小
Notice that when I resize it will actually tell me the size,
注意，當我調整它時候，會實時顯示字號
see it saying there what size it is?
看到這裡顯示的當前的字號
I can also set the size maybe with this size inspector right here,
還可以通過在這裡，進行字號的修改
type it in exactly.
輸入精確的字號
Maybe 64 by 64, something like that.
先設個 64 x 64
We don't usually do that.
我們通常不這樣做
We want things to be kinda their natural sizes but
我們希望它能夠是原始的大小
just want to show you that there are other inspectors over here.
但這裡只想向你展示有其他的方法
So we have this 7.
所以我們有這個 7
Now when this 7 is pressed, what do we want to happen?
當 7 被按下的時候，會發生什麼呢？
What we want.
我們想要的是
Numbers just start appearing up here in the display, right?
數字出現在需要展示的地方
So that's something our controller is going to have to do.
這就是我們的控制器必須處理的
So, when we touch this button, we kinda want this button to send a message to
當我們點擊這個按鈕，我們想讓這個按鈕發送信息到
our controller, and we do that the exact same way as we did this one,
我們的控制器，跟之前的方式一樣，
we hold down control, drag into our code.
我們按住 Ctrl，然後點擊拖動它到代碼中
When we let go though, we're not going to an outlet connection this time,
當我們松開時候，這回我們要的不是 outlet 這個連接，
because I dont want an instance variable here, what i want is a method, right?
因為我不想要個實例變量，我要的是一個方法對吧？
A function on my class, a method, everyone understand the word method I hope,
我類里的一個函數，方法，我想大家都知道 「方法」 這個詞的含義，
okay, so we want it to send an [INAUDIBLE] message to our control board, so
我們想讓它發送一個消息給控制板
I'm going to pick" action", [COUGH] losing my voice here.
所以我選 "action" ,[咳嗽]，今天有點失聲
Bad time to have a little cold, but.
關鍵時刻有點感冒……不過還好
[SOUND] So I'm doing an action so
所以在這裡我選了 action
an action is a little different than a outlet, okay?
action 跟 outlet 略有不同
An outlet means an instance variable or
outlet 代表一個實例變量
property, action means create a method for me.
或者是一個 property ，action 則是為我創建了一個方法
So again it wants to know the name of the method.
所以緊接著它要我輸入方法的名字
So what does this thing do?
這個方法要做什麼呢？
Well when I press seven, it appends a digit onto the end of
當我按 7 的時候，
whatever's already in the display, so I'm going to call it append,
不管原先顯示著什麼，都在後面加個 7，所以我應該叫它 append...
I could call it append seven, but I'm actually going to call it append digit,
本來應該叫做 append 7，但我還是選擇 appenDigit，
because I want to have one method that all of my buttons use.
因為我想所有的按鈕都使用一個方法
All right?
懂了嗎？
I don't want to, copy and pasting a bunch of methods, that would be really bad code.
我不想複製粘貼一堆雷同的方法，那樣只會把代碼變得一團糟
But if I'm gonna have one method,
相反我僅僅使用一個方法，
then I need to know which button is sending me this message, okay?
所以我就需要知道是哪個按鈕發送的這個消息，對吧？
Luckily, when you haven't actioned a message being sent here,
幸運的是，當你從這裡發出消息前
you can specify that it has arguments, you see right here where it says arguments?
你可以規定它有沒有參數，你看這裡它寫著 arguments 了麼？
And it can have no arguments or it can have the sender.
你可以選擇沒有參數，或者是 sender
Which is the button here as the argument.
sender 的意思就是把這個按鈕當作參數
The only tricky thing here is, and I'm not sure why they did this in Xcode.
這裡有點詭異，我不懂 Xcode 為什麼要這樣處理
Hopefully, they'll change it in the future.
希望他們以後能改進下
By default, the type of that argument, which is right here, is anyObject.
就是參數的默認類型是 anyObject
Now, we're gonna talk about anyObject next week.
下周我們會講什麼是 anyObject
But, we don't want anyObject here.
不過在這裡我們肯定不要 anyObject
We know that the sender is a UIButton,
我們知道 sender 其實是 UIButton，
So I picked, click this little blue thing and switch this to UIButton.
所以點這裡選擇 UIButton
When you're doing your homework, if you forget to switch that to UIButton,
如果你做作業的時候，忘了選擇 UIButton，
you'll be sad, okay.
你就悲劇了.
So don't forget.
所以，別忘了哦
And obviously the event that the message is gonna be sent on, touch up inside,
然後很明顯，觸發事件應該選為 touch up inside，
just means the user touched on this button and the touch went up.
意思是你手指點擊的時候落在按鈕的範圍內
While it was still inside the button.
而手指抬起來時也還在按鈕的範圍內
That's all a touch up inside means there.
這就是 touch up inside 的意思
All right so when I connect this,
當我點了 connect 以後，
I'm gonna get a method with one argument which is a sender which is a UIButton.
我就得到了一個方法，有一個參數，類型是 UIButton
So let's take a look.
讓我們看一下
So here's your first method declaration in SWIFT, okay?
它就是你的第一個 Swift 聲明的方法
Again it's got this little IBAction thing which is kinda like IBOutlet.
同樣這裡有一個叫 IBAction 的東西，跟 IBOutlet 類似
It puts a little dot in the gutter.
左邊有一個小圓點
Okay? So that you can
這樣你就可以看見它連的是哪裡
see what this thing is connected to.
So this is the normal, Swift method syntax.
這個就是 Swift 定義方法的標準語法
Starts with func because function,
以 func 開頭，這是 function 的縮寫
basically that method is a function in class.
它就是我們類里的一個方法了
[COUGH] Here's the name.
這是它的名字, AppendDigit
AppendDigit.
這是它的名字，AppendDigit
And then in parentheses, all the arguments separated by commas.
在括號里，所有參數都用逗號分隔
We only have one argument, though.
我們這只有一個參數
Here's the name of the first argument.
這個是第一個參數的名字
That's the name we're going to use to access it inside of our method, and
我們在方法里就要用到這個名字，
here is the type.
這是它的類型
Okay? It's a UIButton.
懂了麼？類型是 UIButton
I, notice no exclamation point there, by the way.
順便提下，要注意到這裡是沒有嘆號的
Okay if this had a return value, if this method returned something this one doesn't
雖然這個方法沒有返回值，但如果
[COUGH] but if it returned something, it would look like this arrow the return type
如果它有的話，這裡就寫這樣的箭頭
okay so that's how you specify a return type.
這樣就定義了它的返回類型
Okay, pretty simple the syntax and then inside here we just type,
看見了麼？非常簡單的語法
well whatever we want this thing to do when one of these buttons is touched.
繼續看我們的函數，當點擊了其中一個按鈕，
So what do we want it to do?
我們要讓它幹甚麼
Well, okay, first of all before we do that, let's go ahead and make more of
在此之前，我們先多弄幾個按鈕
these buttons because I need seven, eight, nine, four, five, six, all this.
我們還需要其他的按鈕，4，5，6 等等等等
So let's copy and paste the button.
我們可以複製粘貼這些按鈕
When I copy and
當我複製粘貼這些按鈕
paste the button, notice I'm using the blue lines to put it perfectly lined up.
注意我用這些藍線來對齊
Okay, also notice that it there also sending this message.
而且它們都同樣發送這個消息
All right, see how their both sending the message, because when I copy and
它們發送同樣這個消息是為什麼呢
paste, it copied that aspect of it as well.
因為拷貝按鈕的時候連同這些信息也一起拷貝了
So there's another one, I could select all three of these and
可以一次選三個，一起拷貝
copy and paste, okay, I could select all six of these and copy and paste.
6 個一起選
So I can quickly make, my entire keypad.
這樣快速得把鍵盤造出來了
Just need to edit the title.
只需要改改 title
Now, if while I'm editing these titles, sometimes you're clicking around in
如果你像現在這樣，做些改動，點來點去
here and, you know, you're not a very accurate clicker.
不小心沒點准
[LAUGH] Or, you know, you just get out, out of control clicking here, and oh,
手一滑把控件拖飛了
you moved it out of the way.
Okay?
怎麼辦？
No problem, you can just put it right back in.
沒關係，只要把它再拖回原地
Okay, use the blue lines to your advantage.
那些藍色的輔助線會幫你個大忙
And we'll put our zero down here.
把 0 放在這
And I don't need these buttons so I'm just hit, selecting it, hitting delete.
選中這些，按下 Delete，我們就可以把不需要的按鈕刪除
That's how you can get rid of something.
就這麼刪東西
And I promised I was gonna put these all on blue lines, so I'm gonna do that.
我剛才說過要把它們對齊藍線
I'm gonna put it right underneath the zero.
把它們放在 0 標籤控件的底下
So here's a blue line that means underneath the zero, and
這條藍線就表明我可以放在標籤底下
then I'm going to put at this edge.
讓它對起左邊這條藍線
So now you can see that the blue lines are not just the edges, but
你可以發現，這些藍線不僅在調整邊緣的時候出現
they are other objects, like the other objects in the keypad and
在調整其他對象，比如這些按鈕的時候，它們也會出現
also now the title, the display rather at the top.
同樣，標題，標籤這些也同樣受用
So I've got all these buttons, they're all sending this message append digit.
現在按鈕齊了，它們都發送 appendDigit 這個消息
So I need to figure out which one is sending it,
所以我就需要分辨出是哪個按鈕發送的消息
so that I can do the right thing.
然後針對性的做相應的功能
So let's start writing some code inside the method.
現在讓我們來往這個方法里添加代碼
So the first thing I'm going to do is declare a local variable,
首先，我要聲明一個局部變量
it's just a local variable inside this method.
就是方法內部的局部變量
I'm going to do that by saying let digit equal.
輸入 let digit =
So I want this local variable to be the digit that was pressed.
我想讓這個局部變量表示我們輸入的數字
Okay.
我想讓這個變量表示我們輸入的數字
So, first thing that's quite different here is, what's let?
這裡值得注意的是，這個 let 是什麼？
Okay?
Why isn't this var, right?
為什麼不是跟上面那個一樣的 var ？
Cuz var means variable, what the heck does let mean?
因為 var 是變量的意思，那 let 是什麼鬼？
Well let is exactly the same as var except it's a constant.
其實 let 跟 var 差不多，只不過 let 代表常量
Which means you're going to sign this right off the bat, and
意味著一旦你為它設置了初值
it's never going to change in this method.
它在這個方法內就再也不能被改變了
Now Swift makes a big deal about this, and
這在 Swift 里很重要
I love this feature, because if I'm reading this code,
我大愛這個特性，因為當我讀代碼的時候，
I know the digit is never going to change all, this might be, you know.
我知道它不會變，而上面那個（var）會變
It might have a dozen lines of code.
假設你的方法里有幾十行代碼，
Which by the way,
順便提一下，
you shouldn't have very many methods, with many more lines of code then that.
你最好別在一個方法裡面塞太多的代碼，
Okay? You want people to be able to
你應該讓人清楚明瞭的知道你這個方法要做的是什麼事情
kind of see what a method's doing.
You can use other methods,
你可以添加其他的方法，
call other methods if you need to get more code in there.
然後通過調用那些方法來實現更多的邏輯
so.
回過頭來
Here I can de-,
rely on that not changing.
因為有了這個 「不變」 的性質，
That's big for readability.
代碼的可讀性得到了很大的提升
You'll be surprised how much more readable it makes the code, to know that this is a,
你會驚嘆僅僅知道哪些是變量，哪些是常量，就會對代碼的可閱讀性帶來這麼大的提升
local variable, but it's constant.
Only set at the beginning.
只需要聲明的時候加個關鍵字就行
Yeah. Is there a reason, constants and
[學生提問] 對於像變量、常量這些東西，這裡為什麼都用相同的命名規範？
like, variables have the same naming convention.
[學生提問] 對於像變量、常量這些東西，這裡為什麼都使用相同的命名規範？
Since [UNKNOWN] like Java there.
因為比如說 Java 會用 「全部大寫」 或者 「全部小寫」 來區別這些概念
Like the naming conventions like all caps or lowercase.
Yeah. So, yeah.
[提問完畢]
The question is, why don't I call digit like all caps digit, or
這位同學的問題是，為什麼不把 digit 寫成 DIGIT，
something like that, so I know it's a constant.
以此來區分它是不是常量
That would be a programming style thing.
這算是編程風格的問題，
Generally in Swift they don't do that.
但在 Swift 里，我們通常不這樣做
And, I'll show you why that is in a moment.
我之後會給你們演示，
Why you don't really need to do that.
為什麼我們不需要通過玩弄命名規範來區別這些概念，
Because you can very quickly find out the declaration of
因為你可以非常快速的找到每個變量的定義，
any symbol anywhere with one click, and you'll see that.
只需要點一下鼠標就一目瞭然
Good question though.
是個好問題
All right, so I wanna let the digit, equal the number that's on the,
所以，接下來我要 let digit = 被觸發的按鈕上的那個數字
the sending button.
So I'm gonna have to send a message to this button.
所以我要向那個按鈕發送一個消息
Okay? Gonna have to somehow access this button.
對吧？我們得訪問這個按鈕對象
So I'm gonna have to do sender, something.
我就打 sender 然後..
Give me what your title is, okay?
拿到它的 title 對吧？
So this is a good time to talk about the documentation.
現在就是講講文檔的好時機了
[COUGH].
[咳嗽]
Because being a good iOS developer,
想要成為一名好的 iOS 開發者，
really demands that you are good at navigating the documentation.
熟練地使用文檔是必須的
Luckily, the documentation is really well plugged in to Xcode.
幸運的是，Xcode 已經完美地嵌入了文檔支持
For example, if I wanna find out about button,
比如，我想看看按鈕的文檔
all I need to do is hold down the option key.
我只要按住 option 鍵
Okay?
And watch what happens now.
看見有什麼變化麼？
As I mouse over things,
當我的鼠標移動到文本上方時，它們底下就會出現一條藍色的虛線
everything, it turns blue with a dashed blue line under it, okay?
If I click on it,
如果我點擊
it gives me a little blurb from the documentation about this thing.
它就彈出一個文檔的摘要
So it's saying, you know, here's, button is a class.
它說這是 button， 這是一個類，
Here's its inheritance.
這裡有它的繼承關係
Here's a little bit of what it does.
這裡是關於它的功能
And really awesome at the bottom here,
最棒的是在最後這裡，
here's a link that takes you to the detailed documentation.
這是一個指向詳細文檔的鏈接
So I'm gonna click this little link right here.
我點擊這個鏈接
It's going to be up a documentation window, with UIButton in it, hello?
它就打開了 UIButton 的文檔窗口……咦？
Did I not click that right thing here,
我沒點錯吧？
oh I hope I don't have a network issue here.
不會是網絡出問題了吧..
hm, okay well, I guess I'm not connected to the network,
好吧，我猜我的網絡出問題了
that's the problem, so it's getting this off the network.
果然，沒有聯上網。
Okay so.
好吧
Imagine that there were documentation here and, it would have along this side here
那就想象一下，文檔出現在了這裡
on the left all the instance variables or properties and methods of u i button.
在窗口的左邊，就會出現很長的一列關於 UIButton 的屬性，變量，方法什麼的
And you could click on any one, and
你可以點擊它們
in there we'd have a full description of it here.
然後就可以在這裡看見完整的描述
And all the types that it referenced you could click on it here, and
所有文檔間的引用你都可以點擊，
basically it's a hyper linked documentation [UNKNOWN].
它本質上就是一些文檔間的超鏈接，
As you can imagine.
你可以想象得到的
I'll try to get the networking working on Wednesday and we'll take a look at this.
我爭取在下週三把網絡問題搞定，到時候我們就能一睹芳容了
But if I was looking in here,
假設我能看到文檔的話，
I'd look down in the section that says getting the button's current state, and
我會在這裡找到一些如何獲取 UIButton 狀態的信息
I'd find that there is an instance property there called current title.
我會找到一個叫做 currentTitle 的屬性
Okay? It's unfortunate I'm not going to
很遺憾沒能演示這個流程
link these things.
But.
不過問題不大
So how do we access, property or call a method in another object,
那麼怎麼訪問到一個對象的屬性、方法呢？
will look exactly the same whether you call it a method or
答案是，訪問屬性和調用方法的方式是一模一樣的
accessing a property, which is you use dot.
訪問屬性，你用點(.)
Okay. It's the same syntax that's used in
這跟大多數語言是一樣的，都用點號來訪問成員
a lot of languages is to, to do dot.
And so when you do that, Xcode is going to say, oh,
當你在 Xcode 里打一個點的時候，它就說，吶，
well, here's all the things button knows how to do.
這裡是所有 UIButton 可訪問的成員
Okay?
看見了麼？
And as you can see, button knows how to do a lot of things.
你可以發現，UIButton 能做很多事情，
Because it inherits from a class, it inherits from a class,
這是因為它繼承於一個類，它的父類又繼承於另一個類，不停繼承
it inherits from a class, that all have lots of methods in them.
所以累積起來就有很多方法可供調用
So when I looked at that documentation.
所以當我查看了文檔以後，
I've found that current title was the thing I wanted.
我知道 currentTitle 這個屬性正是我想要的
Now notice as I start to type a c, it's already cutting down
注意這裡我打個字母 c，它會幫我過濾出那些開頭是 c 的選擇
the things that could be starting with a c, and then c u, they cut down even more.
然後接著打 cu，它有棒我過濾掉了一些
I can type tab, to get to the first ambiguity point, then I can type t.
我可以按 Tab 鍵，前進到第一個歧義點，然後接著打 t
Okay?
And then tab again, and I'm here at currentTitle and then I can press return. Okay?
然後再敲 Tab 鍵，得到 currentTitle，然後按 Enter 鍵
So there it is.
好了
digit = sender.currentTitle
so, what's going on here in terms of the sender title.
我們現在拿到了 sender 的 currentTitle 了，然後呢？
Let's go ahead and print this out to the console just to see what's going on.
我們把它在 console（控制台）中打印出來，看看它裡面是什麼東西
So I'm gonna println.
這裡使用 println 函數
At which is a function, a global function that takes a String.
它是一個全局函數，以一個 String 為參數
So I give it a String.
所以我就給它一個 String
And inside that String, I'll type mm,
在 String 里，我打
digit equals and now I wanna embed the value of digit in this String.
"digit = "，我想把 digit 的值嵌入到這個 string 裡面
And Swift has a really cool feature which is backslash open parentheses
這裡介紹一個 Swift 很酷的特性，就是，
close parentheses.
如果你在字符串里里放進這個 "\()"，然後你就可以在括號裡面放入一個表達式
If you put that in a String, and then inside there you put some expression, then
it will evaluate that expression turn it into a String, and embed it in the String.
Swift 就會對這個表達式求值，然後把值轉換成 String，最後嵌入到那個字符串里
Okay, so its really easy to println values by
所以用這個 "\()" 語法可以很方便的 println 一個對象的值
using this backslash parenthesis. Okay?
So let's go ahead and run and
現在讓我們編譯運行然後
see what happens when we press these buttons to see what kind of result we get.
看看我們按這些按鈕的時候會打印出什麼結果
It's not going to be quite what we expect, but let's see.
結果可能會跟預期的有所不同，
Alright so, here's our UI we got our buttons that's a good start.
好咧，這裡是我們的 UI，有了一些按鈕，看起來不錯
And now, and console, where's the console?
但是控制台呢？輸出結果的控制台去哪了？
Watch this. I'm going to press a button five.
看好了，當我點擊 5 按鈕的時候
The console appears at the bottom here.
控制台就在下面出現了
See this down here.
看見了嗎？在底欄這裡
This is the console.
這就是控制台
And it's saying digit equals, hm, optional five.
這裡顯示了， digit 等於……呃……Optional("5")
Okay.
好吧
How about a nine?
那 9 呢？
They're all optional.
也是 Optional 的
What the heck is going on here? Okay.
這是什麼鬼?
This is crucial to understanding Swift.
接下來我們將要理解一個 Swift 里的重要概念
This is probably the most important thing to understand that
這個概念初學者常常會搞錯，但在 Swift 里它非常特別十分重要
people don't quite get right from the start.
這個概念初學者常常會搞錯，但在 Swift 里它非常特別十分重要的
So we're really going to focus here on understanding what
所以接下來我們集中精力，好好的理解這個 Optional 到底是什麼意思
optional means right there.
Okay?
注意聽咯
So let's go back to our code.
先回到代碼
And look at this, oh and by the way it, when the console appears down here,
看這個，對了，順便提一下，當控制台出現了以後，
you can make it go away with this little button, or
你可以用這個按鈕把它隱藏掉，或者
you can just drag it out of the way okay?
也可以用鼠標把它拖走
But sometimes it's nice to have that console still there, so
不過讓它一直顯示在那裡也挺好的，
you can look at your output while you're you know reacting to whatever you found,
你可以隨時看見你的輸出，及時察覺問題
in fact we will leave that up there, so you can see the optionals.
我就不隱藏它了，讓你可以看見我們現在要講的 Optional
Alright, so, what's going on here?
言歸正傳
Well, what's happening here is, well, first of all,
首先，
don't you find this a little bit odd, let digit, I didn't put a type.
你有沒有發現一個奇怪的地方？ 這裡 let digit = …… 我並沒有給 digit 一個類型
You see that?
看到麼？
How, what type is digit?
那這個 digit 到底是什麼類型呢？
Okay, well there's no type in there, no type information whatsoever, so.
你可能會想，這裡沒有指定任何類型，難道 Swift 支持無類型變量？
Does Swift have untyped variables?
No, it's exact opposite.
錯！恰恰相反
Swift is very strongly typed. Okay.
Swift 是非常非常強類型的語言
All variables have a type.
所有變量都有它的類型
You have to specify type.
你必須規定一個類型
But, Swift is also incredibly good at what's called type inference.
然後，Swift 有一個非常強大的特性，叫做類型推導
So it can infer the type from the context.
這樣它就能通過當前上下文來推斷出變量的類型
So here I let digit equalwhatever this is, this currentTitle, and
所以，當我寫 digit = ... 無論我等號後面寫什麼，這個 currentTitle，
so it just made digit be the same type as this.
它都能將 digit 設置成等號後面那個東西的類型
Okay.
懂了麼？
Now back to the question earlier, so what type is that?
回到之前的問題，那麼這個到底是什麼類型？
Well, if I hold down option, okay, just like we used option to
我可以按住 Option 鍵，就像查看文檔那樣，
go look into the documentation, we can also option click on our own variables.
我們也可以按住 Option 來點擊我們的變量，
To see are they constant?
看看它是常量還是變量
Are they variables?
它們是變量麼？
And what type are they?
還可以看看它們是什麼類型?
So watch this.
看這個
Option click.
按住 Option 然後點擊
It says digit is of type String question mark.
它說，digit 是 「String?」 類型的
Okay? String question mark.
嗯，String 後面有個問號
That question mark means optional.
這個問號的意思是 —— 「Optional（可選）」
So there is a type in Swift, it's a type, called optional.
在 Swift 裡面，有一種類型，叫做 optional
Okay. Optional, that type can have only two values.
Optional 這種類型，只有兩個值
One value is not set.
一個值叫：未設
Okay, this optional is not set, there has never been set or someone has
代表著這個值還沒有被任何人設置過，或者，有人故意把它設置成了 「未設」 狀態
set it to the not set state, they unset it if you want to think about it that way.
So optional one value is not set, we call that there's a, symbol for
當一個 Optional 的變量是 「未設」 狀態時，
it in here called nil, N, I, L, okay?
有一個符號用來表示這個狀態，這個符號叫做 nil, N, I, L.
That means not set, that's the value of an optional not set.
nil 就是 「未設」 的意思，就是 optional 變量在 「未設」 狀態下的值
That's the only thing nil means in Swift is option this is an optional,
在 Swift 里，nil 只有這一個意義，就是說這個變量是 Optional 的，
the value of an optional that is not set.
而且它的值是 「未設」
What's the other value that an optional could have well the other value is.
那 Optional 的另一種值是是什麼呢？
Something, it's set to something, okay.
「有值」，就是說它被設置賦了一個值
And the type of that something is what,
那 「有值」 的這個值，是什麼類型呢？
is specified next to the question mark String.
就是 「?」 前面那個東西代表的類型
So really you can almost think of the question mark there, that's the type
所以，你可以這樣想：
optional, and that String to the left is just saying if this optional is set,
問號左邊的那個 String，就表示，如果這個 Optional 變量被賦了值的話，那麼它的類型就是 String
what type of thing is it set to, in this case a String.
So we would call this an optional String.
所以，我們可以稱其為 「Optional String」
But it's really an optional, it's not a String that can be nil,
但是它實際上確確實實是 Optional 類型的，它不是一個可以為 nil 的 String
it's an optional that can be a String.
它是 Optional 類型，只不過可以被賦值為 Stirng
Everybody cool with that sentence?
好好理解這句話
That's an important sentence to understand, okay.
理解這個句子和含義非常非常關鍵
So, this got to be an optional because this currentTitle method right here,
所以在這裡，currentTitle 返回的值肯定是 Optional 類型的
returns an optional String, let's look at that.
我們來看看
So I'm going to press Option down here, click.
按住 Option 點 currentTitle
Look at this, this is the documentation for it.
看，這是它的文檔
It's an instance variable a, a, property on UIButton.
這是一個實例變量，UIButton 的屬性
Name is currentTitle.
名字是 currentTitle
The type is String, question mark.
類型是 「String?」
And this little get means it's read-only.
而這裡的 「get」 表示這個是只讀的
I can only get the currentTitle.
我只能 get（讀取值） currentTitle
I can't set it, there are other ways to set a button's title.
但是我不能 set （寫入值），有其他方式 set 這個按鈕的 title
You can't set it with this method or this property.
你不能通過這個方法或者屬性 set 這個 title
So it's an optional, so that's why this ended up being an optional all right.
所以這是一個 optional，這就是為什麼它最後也是 optional
Well, that's all wonderful.
嗯，這非常不錯
How do I get the String?
那我該如何獲取這個 String 呢？
I don't want it optional, I want that button's String.
我不希望它是 optional 的，我要的是這個按鈕的 String
And the way you do that is you unwrap the optional, meaning you look in there and
方法就是解包這個 optional，意思是你打開這個它找到裡面的東西，
get the val, the associated value, with exclamation point, okay.
用 「!」 就可以獲取到它的值
What happens if I put that exclamation point there?
如果我把感嘆號放在這裡會怎麼樣？
Well first of all, let me show you that when I put that exclamation point,
首先我先會展示給你們看，當我把感嘆號放在這裡
look what happened to digit, I'm Option-clicking on digit.
看看會有什麼變化，我現在點擊數字 我按 Option 然後點擊這個 digit
It's not an optional anymore.
它不再是 optional 類型了
Digit turned to a String because I unwrapped the optional that
digit 變成了 String，因為我把 optional 解包了，
came back from currentTitle, got the String out of there.
從 currentTitle 里得到了 String
But what happens if this is nil?
但是如果這是個 nil 值會怎麼樣？
What happened if this optional is nil?
如果 optional 是 nil 會怎樣呢？
In other words the button optional has never been set, crash, 'kay,
換句話說，就是這些 optional 類型的按鈕沒有 set 值會怎樣？對的，程序會崩潰
crashes your program, so if you use exclamation point to unwrap an optional,
所以如果你使用 "!" 號來解包一個 optional 的時候
and that optional's current value is not set, nil, then it will crash your program.
並且這個 optional 的 currentTitle 沒有設值，為 nil 的時候，你的程序會崩潰
Now a lot of you might be like whoa, I'm, my products are gonna be crashing all over
現在你們中的不少人肯定在想，我的程序將會整天 crash 掉，
the place and, because there's a lot of optionals in iOS, I mean a lot, okay?
因為 iOS 有著非常多的 optional，非，常，多
Most things are probably optionals, because most things, it make sense,
大部分東西都是 optional 的，因為大部分東西都是有意義的
they can be in an not set state at some point.
某些時候它們會處於 「未設」 狀態
And yeah, in this case though, maybe you want your program to crash, okay?
在這個情況下，說不定你就希望你的程序 crash？對不對？
You might want your program to crash, because if you had a button, that never
你也許就是希望自己的程序 crash，因為如果你有一個按鍵，
had its title set, and it's sending a pen digit to your controller, you probably
但是它的標題從未被 set，並且它傳了一個數字給你的 controller，你也許
wanna have that crash, so you can find that bug, before you ship your program.
想在你的程序見客戶之前，你就能找到 bug，所以你希望它 crash
You see why sometimes fra, crashing is good?
現在你知道為什麼有時候程序 crash 是個好事吧
Now if you don't wanna crash, there's a way to get around that as well.
現在如果你不想你的程序 crash ，這裡有一個方法來解決
And I'll show you that a little bit later.
我等一下下展示給你們看，
But for now understanding that that's what this exclamation point does.
但是現在，先弄明白這個感嘆號是幹甚麼的
It unwraps that optional and crashes if it's nil.
它解包了 optional，如果它是 nil 就 crash
But if it's not nil, it gets to the String or
但如果不是 nil，它是得到 String 或者
whatever the optional type is out of there for you.
其他的 optional 解包後的類型？
So now let's go ahead and run again and
所以讓我們繼續，重新運行一次，
we're gonna see that digit equals is gonna say the number, 'kay?
我們將看看是不是能得到 「digit = 」 對應的數字？
It's got the String off the currentTitle, no more optional in there, okay?
我們得到了 currentTitle 的 String，不再是 optional 的類型了
Good?
看上去不錯
All right, so, now, what are we gonna do with that digit?
好的，現在，我們要用這些 digit 做什麼呢？
We got the digit,
我們已經能得到了數字
we want to append it onto the end of this display right here, okay.
我們希望按的數字能顯示並附加在這裡的末尾
And so let's just do that by saying display, dot.
所以讓我們輸入 display.
Now, again, if we have the documentation,I'd go look in the documentation and
現在繼續，如果我們查文檔
it would say oh, there's a property on UILabel, which is what display is,
它會告訴我們，UILabel 有一個屬性，這個屬性告訴我們 display 是什麼，
display is a UILabel.
負責顯示 UILabel 應該顯示的什麼
There's a property and it' called text.
這個屬性叫做 text
See it right there?
就在這裡
And actually, you can even see right here, the type of that, it's an optional as
而且實際上，輸入這個，你能在這裡看到，這是一個 optional
well, because this label's text might not have been set either, okay?
所以這個 label 的 text 應該還沒有設值
So it has to be an optional String, okay?
所以這裡是 optional String
So I'm just gonna set that equal now, display that text as an optional, so
所以我現在要用等號設值，顯示的 text 作為一個 optional
what values can I send it to,set it to?
什麼值可以設給它？
I could set it to nil, that would be legal because it's an optional,
我可以設成 nil，因為它是一個 optional，所以它是完全合法的
see, no warnings, no errors.
看，沒有警告也沒有錯誤
That would clear out that display.
這將什麼也不顯示
It would not be set to anything, or
它不能設值成其他東西，
I can set it to a String because it's an optional String.
我能給它設一個 String 值，因為它是一個 optional String
So I'm going to set it to a String and the String I'm going to set it
所以我將把它設值一個 String
to is display.text, what's currently in there, plus digit, okay?
這個 String 我設置成 display.text ，這裡加個數字
So I'm going to append that digit on.
這樣子就能附加數字上去了
Let's get rid of that.
讓我們擺脫刪掉這句
Okay, now, this has an error here.
好吧，現在又有一個錯誤
Why does this have an error?
這個錯誤是為什麼呢？為什麼這裡有個錯誤呢？
Anyone volunteer why this is an error?
有誰自願回答這裡為什麼有個錯誤？
See it's pointing right here.
發現錯誤指向這裡
There's an error, back there.
這裡有個錯誤，後面那位同學回答
The display.text is an optional String.
display.text 是一個 optional String
Bingo. Because display.text right here is not
答對了，因為這裡的 display.text 它不是個 String，
a String, it's an optional, and you can't add a String to an optional.
你不能將一個 String 後附加一個 optional
You can only add Strings to other Strings.
你只能將一個 String 附加在另外的 String 上
So we need to turn this into a String by unwrapping it.
所以我們通過解包 optioanl，將 optioanl 轉變為 String
And again, yes, this would crash if the display currently has nothing in it,
對的，這個東西會 crash，如果 display 沒有值
it's not set, okay?
現在還沒有設值
Are we cool with that?
大家都瞭解這個了吧？
So let's run again.
再讓我們運行一次
[BLANK_AUDIO]
[背景音]
All right.
好的
So now 5, oh, it put the 5 on there.
所以現在點擊 5，噢，5 顯示在這裡了
6, excellent.
點擊 6，好極了
It's kinda working.
它能夠工作了
I don't really like that 0 though.
這個 0 在這裡我很不喜歡
That's kinda weak, 0, 5, 6.
這裡就有點問題，5 和 6 前面有個 0
That should not,
這樣子是不對的
that 0 should've gotten cleared out, right, when I first typed that 5.
這個 0 應該在我按下 5 的時候就清除掉
And that's because we really need some way in our controller to know whether we're in
這是因為我們確實需要一些方法讓我們的 controller 知道我們是否在
the middle of typing a number right now.
已經輸入了數字
Because if we're in the middle of typing a number, we want to append, but
因為如果我們在一個已經輸入了數字，我們是希望數字加在後面，
if we're not in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果我們還沒開始輸入數字，
we want to start a new number, right?
我們想要開始輸入的是一個新的數字（而不是在 0 後面附加新數字），對吧？
So, let's do that, and I'm going to do that by adding a property, okay?
所以，讓我們通過添加一個 property 來實現這個效果
var userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber , which you might say,
「var userIsInTheMiddleOfTypingANumber」，你也許會說，
oh my God, that terrible variable, now I have to type that over and over.
天哪，這麼糟糕的變量名字，每次都得這麼輸入還不得累死？
This is the last time I'll ever have to type that, okay?
其實下一次用到這個變量時我並不需要輸入這麼多的
Because Xcode is always going to escape complete it for me, okay?
因為下一次 Xcode 會幫我自動補齊的
So long names are perfectly fine, in terms of typing load anyway.
所以這麼長的名字沒有問題
So I like this name so I'm gonna keep it.
我就挺喜歡這個名字的，就這麼用了.
And it's a bool, okay.
這是一個布爾型數值
So I'm typing its, giving its type.
所以我輸入它，給了它的這個類型
So here's var name type, and notice, look at this little error right here, 'kay.
這個是變量名的類型，注意看這裡，有一個小的錯誤標記
Okay, sometimes you're gonna get errors in Swift that are completely incomprehensible
有時候你在 Swift 會遇到對你來說難以理解的錯誤
to you because you haven't learned enough of Swift.
這是因為你對 Swift 的瞭解還不夠深入
This one's kind of like that.
這個錯誤就是因為這個
You see, it says, class viewController has no initializers.
你看，這裡說，viewController 沒有初始化方法
And that's because, and pay attention, in Swift all properties
請注意，這是因為，在 Swift 里，
have to be initialized when the object is initialized.
當一個對象初始化了，那麼這個對象的所有屬性都必須要初始化
Okay, you can't have a property just sitting around not initialized,
所以你不能用沒有初始化的屬性，
they have to have a value.
它們需要一個值，
Now if they're an optional,
現在，它們是一個 optional，
their value can be nil, but they have to have some value.
它們的值可以為 nil，但是它們必須有值
So we can't have this have no value.
所以我們不能在它們沒有值前使用
Now there's two ways to give it a value.
有兩種方法給它設值，
One is, with an initializer.
一種就是用初始化方法，
Unfortunately, I'm not gonna teach that to you until next week, so
但是不幸的是，這種方法要下周才會教你們，
you can't do it that way.
你還不能用這種方法
Another way is just to say what it equals right here, okay?
所以另外一種方法就是對其直接賦值
And boom, gets rid of all our errors, obviously we don't start out in
一下子，所有錯誤都解決了 很明顯我們
the middle of typing a number,so we're good to go here, all right.
不會一開始就有數字，所以這樣就很好了
So now we have, we know whether the use is in the middle of typing a number.
現在我們就知道了什麼時候輸入了數字
We can go down here and say if the user,
我們能從這裡繼續深入，如果說用戶 ——
now again, I'm just gonna hit Tab to jump past this, maybe a couple times.
再一次，按一下 Tab 跳過這些，可能還要多按幾次，找到這個 ——
But if the user's in the middle of typing a number,
但是如果用戶正在輸入數字，
then we'll do what we were doing before.
那就和剛才我們剛剛做的操作一樣，
Otherwise, we're just gonna set the display.text equal to the new digit we
不然的話，如果我們設置 「display.text = 」
just typed, 'kay?
我們剛剛輸入的新數字
And we're gonna say that the user is now in the middle of typing a number.
這就表示了用戶現在正在輸入數字
Question?
什麼問題？
Why would we have to do [INAUDIBLE] to display it?
[學生提問]
Initialize?
Why did we not have to initialize this?
為什麼我們沒有初始化這個？
That's a fantastic question and
這是個非常棒的的問題，
I'm gonna talk about that on Wednesday cuz there's only one minute left.
我將在週三說這個問題，因為現在只剩下一分鐘了
But that is a great question and it'll also, when I talk about it,
在我下次說到的時候，這依然是個很好的問題
I'm gonna tell you why this is an exclamation point and not a question mark.
我將會說一下為什麼這裡是個感嘆號而不是個問號，
Because I told you that optionals are made with question marks.
因為我之前說過 optional 都是由問號組成的，
So why the heck is this optional?
但是為什麼這個 optional 是這樣的？
Cuz that's what it is, an exclamation point, so we'll talk about that next time.
因為這是個感嘆號，我們下節課再說這個問題，
All right, so let's go ahead and run one last time here.
所以讓我們下次課繼續，
And hopefully this is gonna, this 0 will be cleared out, it is and
我們之前希望這個 0 可以被清掉，看來沒問題，看看這個，
hopefully this will continue to append, it is.
希望這個也可以正常的附加數字，看來也沒問題
So we're in a great spot right here, we've got a calculator,
我們今天已經有了一個不錯的開始，我們已經有一個計算器了，
we can enter numbers in it, next step is, we gotta make it do some calculating, and
我們已經能夠輸入數字了，下一步我們將讓其能夠計算，
we're gonna do that next time so I will see you then.
我們下節課再來實現，大家下節課見
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.
想瀏覽更多？請訪問 stanford.edu